<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Tom Meagher</title>
<subtitle type="text">News nerd-ery</subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com" />
<updated>2016-01-15T15:23:25-05:00</updated>
<id>http://www.tommeagher.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>Tom Meagher</name>
  <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com/</uri>
  <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[U.S. World Cup Roundup for Source]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/07/us-world-cup-roundup.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/07/us-world-cup-roundup</id>
  <published>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/word-cup-roundup/&quot;&gt;OpenNews’ Source blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are few newsroom cliches more stale than the one that says “every night is election night on the sports desk.” But if there’s any grain of truth in it, then the World Cup must be a month of election nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this year’s edition of the World Cup, the analogy holds up a little better, largely because this tournament has been a showcase for some of the best interactive storytelling and data visualization we’ve seen since, well, election night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;predictions-and-prognostication&quot;&gt;Predictions and Prognostication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FiveThirtyEight brought its statistical models to the World Cup, &lt;a href=&quot;http://fivethirtyeight.com/interactives/world-cup/&quot;&gt;handicapping each team’s chances&lt;/a&gt; of advancing from the initial group stage to the knockout rounds and then deeper into the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/538.png&quot; alt=&quot;538&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the New York Times’ Upshot &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/06/19/upshot/world-cup-2014-how-teams-can-advance-to-the-next-round.html&quot;&gt;offered odds&lt;/a&gt; on how likely teams were to progress. But what was even more cool about this piece from the Upshot, at least as I watched it during the workday afternoon matches, was that as each group played its final matches, the app offered a live breakdown of the current standings, along with the time left in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&quot;...we at The Upshot have been obsessed with helping you understand the variety of possible outcomes: what teams must do to win their group, advance or, at the very least, spoil the fun for others.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever a team scored, the app updated within seconds, showing the latest view of who would progress and who wouldn’t. It was a one-stop dashboard for the most pressing question that many fans had: &lt;em&gt;“Right now, will my team make it out of the group stage? And if not, how much time do we have left to try to win?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/kevinq.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Upshot updating&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a similar vein, for the United States’ game against Germany, the Upshot used a square pie chart to show the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/06/25/upshot/984-ways-the-united-states-can-advance-to-the-next-round-of-the-world-cup.html&quot;&gt;984 possible score combinations&lt;/a&gt; that would determine whether the Yanks would keep going in the tournament. During the game, the app updated in real time, showing the current score along with the possible next scores and whether they would help or hurt the U.S.’s chances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;minute-by-minutes&quot;&gt;Minute-by-Minutes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several outlets covered every play in obsessively fine-grained detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Huffington Post’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.huffingtonpost.com/2014/world-cup/matches/brazil-vs-croatia-731767&quot;&gt;live match reports&lt;/a&gt;, powered by a feed from the popular &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.optasports.com/&quot;&gt;Opta sports data vendor&lt;/a&gt; showed the shape of the teams and the location of every shot, along with touches, passing percentage and other stats for every player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/huffpo.png&quot; alt=&quot;HuffPo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chartball.com/&quot;&gt;Chartball.com&lt;/a&gt; also used a feed from Opta to craft &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-game-recaps/#/?g=731811&quot;&gt;post-game recaps for the Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/wsj2.png&quot; alt=&quot;WSJ&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few other apps focused on a single critical play. Leading up to the World Cup, the Wall Street Journal profiled U.S. head coach Jurgen Klinsmann, and as part of the piece, &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/articles/with-his-eye-on-the-world-cup-soccer-coach-jurgen-klinsmann-overhauls-team-usa-1401899734?goTo=wc-goals-intx&quot;&gt;the Journal compared the differing playing styles of several national teams&lt;/a&gt;. The interactive graphic contrasted the straight forward tactics of a country like Portugal (get the ball to Cristiano Ronaldo and let him do his thing) with the elaborate passing of Spain. It’s one thing to read about Spain’s tiki-taka. It’s another altogether to see each of the 42 passes they strung together before scoring against Scotland in a game in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/wsj3.png&quot; alt=&quot;WSJ&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extra-time&quot;&gt;Extra Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past three weeks, scads of great work has been done on other aspects of the Cup. The Washington Post analyzed whether the U.S. was really being punished &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/sports/world-cup-2014/distance-traveled/&quot;&gt;when it drew the worst travel schedule in the tournament&lt;/a&gt;. The Wall Street Journal visualized how the &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-penalty-kicks/&quot;&gt;best penalty kick takers&lt;/a&gt; on each team in the round of 16 tend to shoot (for more on this project, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/all-about-wsjs-penalty-kick-interactive/&quot;&gt;our chat with WSJ news developer Chris Canipe&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two apps illustrated how the players on each nation’s team spend most of their professional life playing together &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/06/20/sports/worldcup/how-world-cup-players-are-connected.html&quot;&gt;on the same club teams&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/sports/leagues-of-the-world-cup/&quot;&gt;in the same leagues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the tournament started, the Guardian collected &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/football/ng-interactive/2014/may/30/-sp-world-cup-kits&quot;&gt;the good, bad, and ugly jerseys from World Cups past&lt;/a&gt; for the 32 teams who qualified. The Guardian US’s interactive team has been tracking the race for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/football/ng-interactive/2014/jun/11/-sp-world-cup-goals-golden-boot-scorers-history&quot;&gt;the Golden Boot&lt;/a&gt;, which goes to the top scorer in the tournament. The app also looks at how often the Golden Boot winner has historically pushed his team to victory in the final.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wall Street Journal took an interesting approach for a static graphic and calculated its own telling metric about the sport. The Journal’s team counted the amount of time each team spent during its group stage games &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/articles/the-world-rankings-of-flopping-1403660175&quot;&gt;theatrically rolling around on the field with mysteriously fast-healing injuries&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While many have done fantastic work so far, the New York Times has released &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.niemanlab.org/2014/06/planning-a-set-piece-how-the-new-york-times-approaches-its-coverage-of-the-world-cup/&quot;&gt;an incredible stream of clever and engaging projects at a rate that is unmatched&lt;/a&gt;. The Times drilled into &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/06/13/sports/worldcup/world-cup-balls.html&quot;&gt;the history and construction of the iconic balls&lt;/a&gt; used at every World Cup since 1930. It employed animation and sound to tell the story of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/06/08/magazine/world-cup-curse-of-maracana.html&quot;&gt;the goalkeeper who made all of Brazil weep in 1950&lt;/a&gt;. It explored &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/06/19/sports/worldcup/goooooooooooooal.html&quot;&gt;the exuberant commentators’ voices that become inextricably tied to the best gooooooooooooooals&lt;/a&gt;. One of the most fun news games of the year is the Times’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://projects.nytimes.com/interactive/sports/worldcup/spot-the-ball/2014/06/30&quot;&gt;Spot the Ball&lt;/a&gt; in which a user has to try to guess where the ball, which has been digitally erased, should be on a photograph. (Trust me, it’s addictive. You have to try it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With three rounds remaining in the Cup and games resuming on Friday, we can only hope that there will be even more great visualization work coming in the next couple of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Did I miss one of your favorite interactive visualizations or World Cup apps? &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/ultracasual&quot;&gt;Tweet at me&lt;/a&gt; or share it in the comments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/07/us-world-cup-roundup.html&quot;&gt;U.S. World Cup Roundup for Source&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on July 03, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[All about the WSJ's penalty kicks interactive]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/07/all-about-wsjs-penalty-kick-interactive.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/07/all-about-wsjs-penalty-kick-interactive</id>
  <published>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/all-about-wsjs-penalty-kick-interactive/&quot;&gt;Open News’ Source blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the days before the World Cup’s knockout stages, with their potential for games to end in shootout finishes, The Wall Street Journal unveiled an app that visualized the tendencies of the top &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-penalty-kicks/&quot;&gt;penalty kicks takers&lt;/a&gt; on the teams advancing in the tournament. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ccanipe&quot;&gt;Chris Canipe&lt;/a&gt;, senior news apps developer on the Wall Street Journal’s interactive graphics desk, talked with me about the thinking behind the project and how he and his colleagues put it together. What follows are edited excerpts from our conversation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-concept&quot;&gt;The Concept&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Cup [interactive coverage] working so well has been completely a product of working with great reporters, who knew what they wanted to do and had great ideas. That makes all the difference. Geoff Foster is one of our main sports guys, and Matthew Futterman, &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/articles/with-his-eye-on-the-world-cup-soccer-coach-jurgen-klinsmann-overhauls-team-usa-1401899734&quot;&gt;who wrote the Klinsmann profile&lt;/a&gt;, wanted to focus on penalty kicks. Geoff Foster had done &lt;a href=&quot;http://online.wsj.com/article/6BE4CA76-48F1-4519-8A12-8E5683D8CAAD.html#!6BE4CA76-48F1-4519-8A12-8E5683D8CAAD&quot;&gt;a video about saving penalty kicks&lt;/a&gt; where he went to the Red Bulls’ practice facility and talked to a goalkeeper about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Penalty kick success rates are very high. It’s almost paper, rock, scissors. You go right, you go left or you go middle.
But very rarely people go middle. (Freakonomics &lt;a href=&quot;http://freakonomics.com/2010/06/14/what-to-do-with-your-penalty-kick/&quot;&gt;looked at this phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; in the run-up to the World Cup in South Africa, four years ago.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/pk2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Penalty kicks&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall success rates are about 78 percent. If you kick to the middle, that goes up 7 percent, because a goalie, they are diving to the left or diving to the right–they don’t have time to think about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a baseball guy. [This penalty kick analysis is similar to] the idea of where to place fielders based on a hitter’s spray pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-data&quot;&gt;The Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a pretty good data provider we work with called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.optasports.com/&quot;&gt;Opta&lt;/a&gt;. They’re particularly good with soccer data. They gave us all kinds of stuff. Included in the game event summaries, they had X- Y- and Z- coordinates for penalty kicks. We were really impressed with the level of detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was really easy to put in a request, “Here’s a list of players, can we get every penalty kick that they’ve ever taken?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some limitations with the data set. Not everybody has a significant body of penalty kicks in their career. (Opta also doesn’t have comprehensive data for players on club teams outside the highest echelons, making it harder to get stats for someone who plays in the Iranian league, for instance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We kind of wanted to do this at the beginning [of the tournament], but the more we played with the data, the more we sketched it out, we saw it would work better with a smaller number of teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[We settled on] two players for each team in the round of 16, but still we have a bunch of the guys in the set who only have one kick. Algeria, we only had one player [with data]. We were hoping for Russia to beat Algeria (to advance out of the group stage) because we had two guys for Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn’t comes as XML or JSON; this comes as a spreadsheet. You get the matchup, the date… X is length of the pitch, Y is the length of the goal side of the field, Z is up and down. [For a goal, you get the] end-Y and end-Z position, and end result or outcome. It’s either a goal, or it’s saved, or it hit the posts or it’s a miss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/gameday.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pitch-by-pitch&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a baseball fan, I think of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/gameday/index.jsp?gid=2014_07_02_phimlb_miamlb_1#gid=2014_07_02_colmlb_wasmlb_1&amp;amp;mode=gameday&quot;&gt;MLB’s pitch-by-pitch Gameday view&lt;/a&gt;.
I always figured that part of [the data collection] was some computer recording the position. But it’s these data vendors [like Opta]. They employ rooms full of people who are watching every event of the game and coding it. That’s really interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran into an issue initially where we had Y-positions that were reversed on the field, because Opta had not corrected–we caught it–which side of the field kicks were being taken from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To catch problems in the data, you go and watch lots of videos and make sure everything is lining up. You find as many of these on YouTube as you can, so you have confidence all of them are correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we got the [corrected] data back [from Opta], we watched maybe 10 kicks, random spot checks. It’s hard to find video of these. You have a shaky cell phone view of people watching on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re working with data that is hand-coded, so any time you’re working with a vendor like this, you’re taking a little bit of a risk. There’s a lot of room for human error in something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual work itself, it was not hard to put together. The hard part was narrowing down and coming up with what we wanted to say with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked really well as a small multiples piece, because you get to compare all of these guys together, especially if they have a large enough sample size, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-penalty-kicks/#/?sel=19054&quot;&gt;Messi&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-penalty-kicks/#/?sel=53645&quot;&gt;Hulk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-penalty-kicks/#/?sel=40720&quot;&gt;Cavani&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s built with D3. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.propublica.org/nerds/item/design-principles-for-news-apps-graphics&quot;&gt;small multiples&lt;/a&gt; approach was sort of obvious from the beginning. Part of the reasoning is that it reflows so easily for mobile. Small multiples rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want to see guys side-by-side. Do guys spread out their kicks? How many guys actually do go to the middle? Most guys go left or right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/img/uploads/article_images/pk1.png&quot; alt=&quot;PKs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s that filter in the top, “Trends Left” or “Trends Right.” Nobody trends to the middle, except for the guys who had two kicks in their set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After launch, &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-game-recaps/#/?g=731815&quot;&gt;that first game&lt;/a&gt;, was a shootout. It almost made us seem prescient. I was sitting at home, watching that game. The Journal main desk tweeted it out. We got a ton of traffic right at that moment. In that first game, you could see penalty kick patterns for &lt;a href=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-penalty-kicks/#/?sel=42565&quot;&gt;Vidal&lt;/a&gt; and Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is definitely not a case where it goes up, and the traffic dies off immediately. All of our stuff, I’m really surprised how much social traffic things are getting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the beauty of the World Cup stuff. It has this sort of long life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://graphics.wsj.com/wc-penalty-kicks/images/goal.png&quot; alt=&quot;An open net&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/07/all-about-wsjs-penalty-kick-interactive.html&quot;&gt;All about the WSJ's penalty kicks interactive&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on July 03, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Things I never learned at newspapers about making news on the internet]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/06/things-i-never-learned-at-newspapers.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/06/things-i-never-learned-at-newspapers</id>
  <published>2014-06-03T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-06-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adapted from a lightning talk I gave at ASNE’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://asne.org/blog_home.asp?Display=1695&quot;&gt;Hacking News Leadership&lt;/a&gt; conference in Austin, Texas in May. You can see my original slides here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haikudeck.com/lessons-from-thunderdome-art-and-design-presentation-CHZ3Wu9ZR4&quot;&gt;http://bit.ly/tdnewslead&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tdome.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Over 21 months at Thunderdome, we created a lot of great projects, from interactive graphics for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://extras.twincities.com/elections/sandyhook/&quot;&gt;Newtown shootings&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sentinelandenterprise.com/webextras/ci_23055737/interactive-people-boylston-street-during-boston-marathon-bombing&quot;&gt;Boston marathon bombings&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sltrib.com/sltrib/news/56473395-78/claims-veterans-lake-salt.html.csp?page=1&quot;&gt;deep-dive data analyses&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twincities.com/nation/ci_25247140/where-insurance-premiums-are-highest-new-health-laws&quot;&gt;visualizations&lt;/a&gt;. They included pieces like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://crime.denverpost.com/&quot;&gt;Our crime map&lt;/a&gt; framework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://data.digitalfirstmedia.com/waffler-pa&quot;&gt;The Waffler&lt;/a&gt; news game&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://data.digitalfirstmedia.com/guns/&quot;&gt;Firearms in the Family&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each of these projects, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thunderdome-data.github.io&quot;&gt;our data team&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://outsidethunderdome.com/2014/04/30/project-thunderdome-staff/index.html&quot;&gt;our colleagues across the newsroom&lt;/a&gt; learned so much. We learned new ways to visualize data and new code libraries for user interaction. We learned about code management and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/05/lessons-code-management-project-thunderdome.html&quot;&gt;how to (and how not to) open source&lt;/a&gt; our work. We learned how to report, design and release smarter, more engaging interactives. As we wrapped things up in our closing days, I realized that some of the biggest lessons from our time at Thunderdome were more cultural than technical, and they were ones we never anticipated in our previous jobs in print-first newsrooms.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/deli.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-internet-is-not-a-deli&quot;&gt;The Internet is not a deli&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first misconception newspaper veterans have is the notion that interactive news teams are simply new-fangled print graphics desks. Although the two roles have skills in common (visual-thinking, smart data presentation), there are enough differences to make the comparison worrisome. Many newsrooms treat their graphics desk like a deli counter. A reporter reports a story and files it on deadline. At that point, an editor looks at it and says, “We should have a graphic for this.” That editor takes a number from the graphics desk, if there is one, and waits for a suitable print-ready image to be sliced to size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mindset, and the idea that interactive news developers should be a support desk, is counter-productive (pardon the pun). This work is too expensive, in terms of time and resources, to follow the old print graphics desk model. Journalist-developers must be woven into the assigning side of the newsroom and involved in stories from the very beginning, not sitting around waiting to pretty things up at the last minute. At ProPublica, the developers on Scott Klein’s news apps team are expected to not only design and build interactives for the web, but also to help with the reporting. They’re involved in the entire process, from start to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hard adjustment for newspaper reporters, who are accustomed to having time to figure out what their story is before filing it at the last possible minute. They need to think on a timeline that allows developers to help. We can build on deadline when news demands, but the rest of the time, we shouldn’t have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took a while for the data team to figure out how to deal with this. We noticed a turning point when we stopped waiting for other desks to pitch ideas on our timetable and began to pursue more of our own projects. Anyone was welcome to join the fun, but we knew if we wanted to get something good done for the 50th anniversary of JFK’s assassination in November, for instance, we’d need to start working on it in August. &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.digitalfirstmedia.com/jfk/&quot;&gt;And it worked&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/team.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hire-new-skills&quot;&gt;Hire new skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we started Thunderdome, there were several roles we weren’t even thinking about that became integral to our online storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the original plan for the newsroom, there was no data team. Thankfully, our editor, Robyn Tomlin, knew we needed one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also didn’t initially think about web design, front-end programming or motion graphics. These were jobs we never had at any of the newspapers I worked at. But without the first two, our data team couldn’t have done a single interactive project. Without our awesome motion graphics designer, our presentations for many of our later projects would have been lackluster, at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expertise that this new style of storytelling demands simply doesn’t exist in most news organizations. Our job is to develop these skills where we can and to hire for them now, and the smart editors will recognize that you’re probably not going to find people with these skills by only posting on journalismjobs.com.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;herd-all-the-cats&quot;&gt;Herd all the cats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a newspaper, the chain of command, established over a century of practice, is very simple and well-known. In our interactive newsroom, it was a little harder to determine sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many of our more ambitious stories, we had contributors from the data team, the design team, the video team and the features, news and sports desks. We’d often be working with reporters or editors at the local DFM papers. Many of our most successful projects crossed traditional department boundaries. But we noticed quickly that it wasn’t which editor should be orchestrating the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one case, we had a really outstanding intern coordinating a project, but there was confusion between myself and another editor as to which of us was really in charge. We learned that projects like these require new levels of collaboration, and that’s not always easy. You need someone who can corral the players across the newsroom, as well as someone in a traditional editor’s role, focused on getting the story right and telling it well. We started to insist that every project have a project manager and an editor, someone calling the shots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; lead a project, but somebody &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; lead.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/break_the_cms.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-need-a-sandbox&quot;&gt;You need a sandbox&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interactive team must have a space outside of the CMS to experiment and to be able to break shit without bringing down the entire system. At one point at Thunderdome, the local papers in our company had at least four CMSes. Trying to build interactives that would painlessly work in each system was a monstrous task. But without a sandbox of our own to experiment in, it would have been impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most CMSes are designed to prevent the kind of monkeying around that this new kind of online storytelling requires. News development teams that do this well all run their own servers, often in the cloud through something like &lt;a href=&quot;http://aws.amazon.com/&quot;&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/a&gt;. This offers the flexibility to try new tools and to iterate at a speed that most corporate IT departments just can’t adapt to. If you’re starting a team from scratch, the very first thing you have to do is &lt;a href=&quot;http://thescoop.org/archives/2014/05/22/how-it-starts/&quot;&gt;give it the tools it needs to succeed&lt;/a&gt;, and an autonomous development sandbox is at the top of that list.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iteration-leads-to-bigger-successes&quot;&gt;Iteration leads to bigger successes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Failure is an option. Our data team was willing to try anything new, knowing that even if it bombed spectacularly, we’d walk away with the know-how to make our next project work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of our most successful apps began as more humble ones. We iterated and used most of what we learned from &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.digitalfirstmedia.com/jfk/&quot;&gt;the JFK project&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.digitalfirstmedia.com/guns/&quot;&gt;Firearms in the Family&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bracketadvisor.com/&quot;&gt;Bracket Advisor&lt;/a&gt; was the second or third iteration of a tool we originally created with our sports desk for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twincities.com/1000/ci_22346309/predict-nfl-playoffs?mobRedir=false&quot;&gt;the NFL playoffs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a daily newspaper, looking back at how well a story succeeded was never even considered. To be fair, when you’re writing quick stories every day, you learn and adapt much faster. When your projects take weeks, or sometimes months, that learning process has to be more deliberate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to good iteration was in our post-mortem reviews. After each deployment, we’d pause to collect our thoughts, to write down what worked and what didn’t and to craft a list of features we’d want in the next project. Then we’d use those ideas over and over again to make our work better.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/culture_is_contagious.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;be-the-journalist-you-want-others-to-become&quot;&gt;Be the journalist you want others to become&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do good work, other journalists will pay attention. Every project was a learning opportunity for our team, for colleagues at Thunderdome and at our local papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big part of our data team’s mission was to evangelize for smart watchdog reporting, strong data analysis and good online presentation. We wanted to share our ideas and to learn from our colleagues. It was gratifying to see others pick up on this, whether it was a producer in Thunderdome embracing &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.documentcloud.org/home&quot;&gt;DocumentCloud&lt;/a&gt; or an editor in Michigan asking for advice on tools for searchable tables and interactive maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we began, we inherited a small email list of a couple dozen local DFM journalists who were data-curious. By the time Thunderdome shut down, the listserv had grown to about 120 people, from San Jose to New Haven. Newspaper journalists want to learn how to do data analysis and develop for the web. A newsroom that supports them in practicing and mastering those skills will reap the benefits. You have to start building that culture.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All images are Creative Commons-licensed. You can see the credits for each of them here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.haikudeck.com/lessons-from-thunderdome-art-and-design-presentation-CHZ3Wu9ZR4&quot;&gt;http://bit.ly/tdnewslead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/06/things-i-never-learned-at-newspapers.html&quot;&gt;Things I never learned at newspapers about making news on the internet&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on June 03, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons in open source code management]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/05/lessons-code-management-project-thunderdome.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/05/lessons-code-management-project-thunderdome</id>
  <published>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/media/cache/29/6a/296a72f3ab7a102515d96829e0ac138a.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lessons from the Project Thunderdome Shutdown&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;            &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://source.opennews.org/en-US/articles/lessons-project-thunderdome-shutdown/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;OpenNews&#39;s Source&lt;/a&gt; blog. This piece ran a few days after the closure of my employer, Digital First Media&#39;s Project Thunderdome.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every time the data team at &lt;a href=&quot;http://outsidethunderdome.com/&quot;&gt;Project Thunderdome&lt;/a&gt; prepared to launch an interactive graphic, a &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CAR&lt;/span&gt; story, or a news app, I’d say to myself something along the lines of, &amp;#8220;As soon as this hits production, we&amp;#8217;ll go back and beef up the inline documentation to save ourselves headaches the next time we try something like&amp;nbsp;this.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, despite our best intentions, we never went back until so much time had passed that we’d completely forgotten just about everything we had tried to&amp;nbsp;do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the Thunderdome data team is not peculiar in this respect. But last month, we were given a pretty good reason to revisit our code one last time. Faced with the demise of our newsroom, we decided &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thunderdome-data&quot;&gt;to open source much of our code&lt;/a&gt; under a permissive &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt; license. In doing so, we hope that our now former colleagues at Digital First Media, the nation’s second-largest newspaper company, can fork and reuse our&amp;nbsp;work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as importantly, we hope journalist-developers in other news organizations will build on our code, so they don’t have to reinvent the wheel every time they want to do something simple that we figured out. And maybe, just maybe, sharing this code, as so many other &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/datadesk&quot;&gt;great&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/texastribune&quot;&gt;news&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wnyc&quot;&gt;organizations&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nprapps/&quot;&gt;have already done&lt;/a&gt;, will encourage more newsrooms to do the&amp;nbsp;same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pbs.twimg.com/profile_images/2957427857/cca3b69ec0a82cbfb05666f79cf3cd04.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;@DFMdata on Twitter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 2, we learned that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.niemanlab.org/2014/04/the-newsonomics-of-digital-first-medias-thunderdome-implosion-and-coming-sale/&quot;&gt;Digital First Media decided to shut down the Thunderdome newsroom&lt;/a&gt;. Among our many duties, the data team&amp;#8211;Peggy Bustamante, Vaughn Hagerty, Nelson Hsu, MaryJo Webster, and me&amp;#8211;built interactive news applications and pursued computer-assisted reporting, on our own and with colleagues across the company’s 75 local newsrooms. After the announcement, we were left scrambling to figure out how to finish a half-dozen projects and how to preserve the code behind our work when no one would be responsible for picking up the pieces after we&amp;nbsp;left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team had six weeks to wrap things up, which seemed like plenty of time. But we had projects that we desperately wanted to finish, like our election news game, &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.digitalfirstmedia.com/waffler-pa/&quot;&gt;The Waffler&lt;/a&gt; or our examination of why &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nhregister.com/general-news/20140512/scope-of-nationwide-heroin-epidemic-unknown-drug-related-death-overdose-data-lacking&quot;&gt;national data on soaring heroin deaths is so flawed&lt;/a&gt;. That left us with a little less than two weeks to clean up our code&amp;nbsp;base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I mentioned to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/kleinmatic&quot;&gt;Scott Klein&lt;/a&gt; that we wanted to prevent nearly two years of work from disappearing, he offered a simple suggestion: open source&amp;nbsp;it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, as we walked out the door of Thunderdome for the last time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thunderdome-data&quot;&gt;we did just that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-we-did-it&quot;&gt;How We Did&amp;nbsp;It&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we had to get permission. Our bosses, editor Robyn Tomlin and managing editor Mandy Jenkins, had been incredibly supportive of the data team and our work from the outset, and they didn’t require much convincing. So we had a brief meeting with our &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CEO&lt;/span&gt;, John Paton, and made our pitch that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.haikudeck.com/open-source-the-dome-inspiration-presentation-lZTwMq34H9&quot;&gt;to not publish our code under an open source license would be a waste&lt;/a&gt;. To his credit, John, &lt;a href=&quot;http://jxpaton.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;who has spoken and written extensively&lt;/a&gt; on how our industry needs to innovate and to invest in digital storytelling, required no more convincing. He gave his approval, and we were off and&amp;nbsp;running. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our next step was to review all of our code that was stuffed into private Github repositories and prioritize projects for release. We put a checklist in a Google Spreadsheet and each member of the team labelled her or his&amp;nbsp;projects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reusable—we had used this code over and over as a template or that we thought others might find&amp;nbsp;useful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just publish—these we’d like to share but were probably discrete and didn’t warrant a lot of additional polishing&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/span&gt;—these were either stories that hadn’t yet published or applications that had a reasonable expectation of being used by our papers for some time, like our crime maps &lt;a href=&quot;http://stpaulcrime.twincities.com/&quot;&gt;in St. Paul&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://crime.denverpost.com/&quot;&gt;Denver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bury it in a swamp—these were so embarrassing or would require such a monumental amount of work to make them presentable, that we preferred to pretend they never&amp;nbsp;happened.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went through scores of repos and categorized them, ending up with about 40 or so that we wanted to release. For each of them, we reviewed all of the code for security and to ensure there was nothing proprietary or worrisome in it. We added a more helpful &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;README&lt;/span&gt; (using a template borrowed from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nprviz&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;NPR&lt;/span&gt; Viz&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nprapps/app-template&quot;&gt;fantastic app-template&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;http://choosealicense.com/licenses/mit/&quot;&gt;an &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt; license&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most reusable projects, we wanted to offer guidance on how someone else might bootstrap it or abstract the code to make it a more generic template. And this is the area where we simply ran out of time and fell&amp;nbsp;short. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because as many of you have probably already thought to yourselves, this whole endeavor was inherently flawed. We made this much, much harder on ourselves than it needed to be, because we did it all backwards. We should have been releasing our code as open source from the outset, in a sane way. But when you&amp;#8217;re pushing code on a news deadline and storing it in private repos, robust documentation is not always the priority that it needs to&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be hard to make the case to executives that open sourcing code isn’t the same as giving away the farm. We benefitted in this regard here, because we had a good track record within the company, and we had a body of work to point to. We could honestly say, “Look at this work. There&amp;#8217;s nothing here that would damage the company, and in fact, if we don’t publish this code, we’d be preventing many people in the company from ever using it again.” That this was our dying wish probably helped seal the&amp;nbsp;deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-we-ended&quot;&gt;What We Ended Up&amp;nbsp;With&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/thunderdome-data&quot;&gt;our new public Github organization&lt;/a&gt; we pushed dozens of projects, built in &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;JS&lt;/span&gt;, a bit of &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;PHP&lt;/span&gt;, and a smidgeon of Python. Among those, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thunderdome-data.github.io&quot;&gt;there are nine in particular&lt;/a&gt; that we think other newsrooms might find most useful, including a balloting tool, an interactive bracket, a profile tool and more. But we still need help to finish the&amp;nbsp;job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use one of these, help us to beef up the documentation and truly abstract it. Fork it and send us pull requests. If you want more advice on how to get started, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/about&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in your own work, start writing good documentation from the start of every project, and don’t wait to open source your code until it’s too&amp;nbsp;late.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2014/05/lessons-code-management-project-thunderdome.html&quot;&gt;Lessons in open source code management&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on May 20, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chasing the 8-hour app]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/10/chasing-8-hour-app.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/10/chasing-8-hour-app</id>
  <published>2013-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2013-10-19T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cross-posted from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sunlightfoundation.com/blog/2013/10/11/opengov-voices-chasing-the-8-hour-app/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sunlight Foundation&#39;s OpenGov Voices blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, &lt;a title=&quot;Hack Jersey&quot; href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hack Jersey&lt;/a&gt; brought a group of journalists and developers together to wrestle with campaign finance data. We thought it would be a good opportunity for many to get their hands dirty and to start thinking about new ways of reporting and building with the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one room of our event at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.njit.edu/&quot;&gt;New Jersey Institute of Technology&lt;/a&gt;, a group of journalists went on a data expedition, learning how to explore reports from the state&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/2013/09/guiding-journalists-through-strange-world-of-money-and-politics/&quot;&gt;Election Law Enforcement Commission&lt;/a&gt;. In another, we gathered developers to try to build a campaign finance app for New Jersey using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sunlightfoundation.com/api/&quot;&gt;Sunlight Foundation&#39;s APIs&lt;/a&gt; in a single work session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We began Hack Jersey about a year ago, starting with some conversations between journalists and developers who wanted to work together to improve news and data in the Garden State. Since then, with the support of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://njnewscommons.org/&quot;&gt;NJ News Commons&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mozillaopennews.org/&quot;&gt;Knight-Mozilla OpenNews&lt;/a&gt;, we sponsored the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sunlightfoundation.com/blog/2013/03/29/opengov-voices-hack-jersey-hackathon-public-data-solving-problems/&quot;&gt;first news-themed hackathon in New Jersey&lt;/a&gt; and several smaller training events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve been eager to take the excitement from the traditional hackathon competition and translate it into projects that news organizations and news consumers can actually use. We wanted our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/event/law-money-and-politics/&quot;&gt;&quot;Law, Money &amp;amp; Politics&quot; hackday&lt;/a&gt; to entice developers to work together to solve a news problem instead of competing against one another. We were psyched to be able to use Sunlight&#39;s APIs in that effort and to have the support of the foundation, which helped sponsor our event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was clearly an interest among developers in this approach. About 15 coders--from computer science programs at local universities, the startup community and nearby news organizations--came to work, and another four helped us plan the project in our pre-hack meetups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the group took shape, we needed to figure out what we wanted to build. We spent almost four hours over two weeks talking and thinking about ideas we solicited from local news organizations. What problem did we want our app to solve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all agreed that campaign finance is a murky, labyrinthine realm and that people in New Jersey could use all the help they could get understanding it. We love the Sunlight Foundation&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.influenceexplorer.com/api&quot;&gt;InfluenceExplorer API and the way it makes&lt;/a&gt; state data, cleaned and cared for by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.followthemoney.org/&quot;&gt;National Institute for Money in State Politics&lt;/a&gt;, accessible. We could spend a whole hack day or two trying to mold our state ELEC data into a more useful format, but InfluenceExplorer and NIMSP has done a lot of that dirty work for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After what we thought was much discussion and tinkering with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tryit.sunlightfoundation.com/influenceexplorer&quot;&gt;API&lt;/a&gt;, we zeroed in on the idea of comparing campaign donations coming from industries into state elections. What industries were backing the most winners in New Jersey? How was campaign spending by industry changing from cycle to cycle? What industries were behind some of our more notable politicians?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;size-full wp-image-56374  aligncenter&quot; src=&quot;http://sunlightfoundation.com/media/2013/10/Hackers-at-Hack-Jersey.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hackers at Hack Jersey&quot; width=&quot;547&quot; height=&quot;392&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hackers at Hack Jersey&#39;s Law, Money and Politics Hack day. Photo by Tom Meagher.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that much decided, our team members volunteered to take certain development roles, and we got ready for the hack day. We imagined a front page with a 30,000-foot-view that would show charts of how much industries have spent on all New Jersey campaigns available in the data, going back more than 10 years. After that, we thought our user could drill in to look at specific industries and how their spending changed from cycle to cycle. Or you could put candidates in specific races side-by-side to see what industries supported them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we quickly realized that the API, which offers access to individual campaign donations by state, only really returns requests for top industry spending across the whole nation. There was no method (yet) to let us grab the top industries in just a certain state or a specific year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the day went on, we hit a few more snags when we realized there wasn&#39;t an easy way through the API to get all the candidates who lost elections. So we downloaded the &lt;a href=&quot;http://data.influenceexplorer.com/bulk/&quot;&gt;bulk data&lt;/a&gt; from Influence Explorer and pulled those candidates out ourselves. With each unexpected misstep, the minutes and hours flew by. In the hopes of finishing a project, we&#39;d shrink the scope and tighten our focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally decided, with a couple of hours left, that we could build a demo app that would let you pick an election cycle in New Jersey, and then browse the available races and see what industries supported each candidate. Two of our developers, who also happen to be the leads for our event sponsor Broadstreet Ads, led the final sprint. They helped pull together a Python web.py framework with Angular.js and Highcharts to power the front end. &lt;a href=&quot;http://hackjersey.broadstreetads.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;We could almost see the finish line&lt;/a&gt;. And then we ran out of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s hard to build anything in 8 hours, much less bring 15 people together to make a single, deep and useful news application. Although we fell short, we had fun and learned a lot in the process for how to do it better next time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;We could have had a better handle on the very wide range of experience and backgrounds our developers brought to the team. By taking a little more time talking about our skills, we could have focused our project more closely on an attainable goal for such a short window of coding. Time is expensive and in short supply. There is no time for indecision.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Double the time spent planning before the event, and then double it again. Although we did a good job of considering the overall vision and anticipating some of the quirks of the data, we needed to set very specific tasks for everyone on the team and make sure people were clear about their roles and comfortable. A large group doesn&#39;t always lend itself easily to collaborative exploration or problem solving. People need to feel like they&#39;re in the mix, especially if they&#39;re giving up a Saturday for a civic hack project.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do more &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pair programming&lt;/a&gt;. With so many developers, we should have put everyone in pairs from the outset, so each person would have a buddy to help spot mistakes and typos that can eat up precious time. We also could have designated experienced developers as leaders for each aspect (back end, front end, design, documentation), who could have helped make some of the design and implementation decisions more quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Read the documentation. Test the methods. It seems so simple, but although we spent a few hours with the Influence Explorer documentation, we still kept finding unexpected nuances in the data it returned, very late in the day. If we had spent more time with it, we could have spotted potential detours more quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an experiment for us. Some experiments don&#39;t work, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/2013/09/developing-a-solution-for-tracking-campaign-giving/%20&quot;&gt;you can learn a lot from failure&lt;/a&gt;. Nearly everyone who participated said they want to work on more news hacking initiatives in the future. Several have said they plan to dig deeper into campaign finance and Sunlight&#39;s APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in our idea? Take a look at the repo, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hackjersey/politics&quot;&gt;fork it and hack away&lt;/a&gt;. We&#39;d love to get others involved, whether you&#39;re from New Jersey or elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we didn&#39;t get as far as we would have liked, it was a good experience for us at Hack Jersey. We got 15 developers thinking about campaign finance and starting to learn the ins, the outs and the possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We couldn&#39;t grow an orchard in a day, but we planted a lot of good seeds. And that&#39;s a pretty good place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/10/chasing-8-hour-app.html&quot;&gt;Chasing the 8-hour app&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on October 19, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diving into data with SPJ]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/04/diving-in-to-data-with-spj.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/04/diving-in-to-data-with-spj</id>
  <published>2013-04-12T17:26:15-04:00</published>
  <updated>2013-04-12T17:26:15-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I had a chance to speak at the Society of Professional Journalists’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spjr1c.org/&quot;&gt;Region 1 Spring conference&lt;/a&gt;, held at Rutgers University in New Brunswick. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/debgalant&quot;&gt;Debbie Galant&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://njnewscommons.org/&quot;&gt;NJ News Commons&lt;/a&gt; and I talked about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/2013/03/11/rounding-up-our-hack-weekend/&quot;&gt;the projects that came out of&lt;/a&gt; our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/&quot;&gt;Hack Jersey&lt;/a&gt; hackathon. Then I laid out a map for building data skills in the newsroom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who attended (and those who didn’t), here are links to some of the tools we discussed and tutorials to start to learn them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slides: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/R1C13DATA&quot;&gt;bit.ly/R1C13DATA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started by sharing examples of data-driven news applications on the web:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crashdatanj.com&quot;&gt;CrashDataNJ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.becauseofus.net&quot;&gt;BecauseofUs.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pancaketheorem.com/stuff/hackjersey/&quot;&gt;Cost of Radiology in New Jersey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/nation/smelting-lead-contamination#explore/&quot;&gt;USA Today’s “Ghost Factories” project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://project.wnyc.org/news-maps/schools-waitlists/&quot;&gt;WNYC schools waitlist map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ProPublica’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://projects.propublica.org/docdollars/&quot;&gt;Dollars for Docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you do this kind of work (or get to Carnegie Hall)? Practice. Practice. Practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief detour on the history of data journalism included a data piece in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guardian.co.uk/news/datablog/video/2013/apr/04/history-of-data-journalism-video&quot;&gt;first issue of the Manchester Guardian in 1821&lt;/a&gt; and the cover of the program for IRE’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mtdukes/status/321331954937122816/photo/1&quot;&gt;first computer-assisted reporting conference in 1993&lt;/a&gt;. And now, to today…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-disciplines-of-data-reporting&quot;&gt;The disciplines of data reporting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collection&quot;&gt;1. Collection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pandaproject.net/&quot;&gt;PANDA Project &lt;/a&gt;- a newsroom warehouse for data, with &lt;a href=&quot;http://pandaproject.net/docs/search-subscriptions.html&quot;&gt;search alerts&lt;/a&gt; when new data arrives	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foiamachine.org/&quot;&gt;FOIA Machine&lt;/a&gt; - a new site to help track FOIA requests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.documentcloud.org/home&quot;&gt;DocumentCloud&lt;/a&gt; - a free tool for journalists to store, annotate, publish and embed PDF documents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For scraping web pages - &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reporterslab.org/scraping-roundup/&quot;&gt;http://www.reporterslab.org/scraping-roundup/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cometdocs.com/&quot;&gt;Comet Docs&lt;/a&gt; - a free service to scrape PDFs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://source.mozillaopennews.org/en-US/articles/introducing-tabula/&quot;&gt;Tabula&lt;/a&gt; - a new project to help make PDF scraping easier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cleaning&quot;&gt;2. Cleaning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My go-to cleaning tool for relatively small data sets (less than, say, 10,000 records) is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openrefine.org/&quot;&gt;Open Refine&lt;/a&gt;. Can’t say enough good things about it. In this blog post are &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2013/02/more-tips-for-using-openrefine.html&quot;&gt;links to my Open Refine class&lt;/a&gt; and several others to get you started.	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twincities.com/thedatamine&quot;&gt;MaryJo Webster&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/26567839/My%20Favorite%20%28Excel%29%20Things.pdf&quot;&gt;“Excel Magic” class&lt;/a&gt; for cleaning data in Excel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For the truly adventurous, check out Dan Nguyen’s great new ebook &lt;a href=&quot;http://regex.bastardsbook.com/&quot;&gt;introducing regular expressions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;analysis&quot;&gt;3. Analysis&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Excel is going to be your favorite tool ever. There are a number of good tutorials on basic Excel and more advanced Pivot Tables &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/2013/01/17/roadmap-to-data-skills/&quot;&gt;listed here&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a link to a great, free online course introducing databases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And don’t forget the formula for percent change = (new-old)/old&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Only for a few more days, you can get 50-percent off of all Excel e-books from O’Reilly here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/R1C13EXCEL&quot;&gt;bit.ly/R1C13EXCEL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;visualization&quot;&gt;4. Visualization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sharon Machlis of ComputerWorld’s great list of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9214755/Chart_and_image_gallery_30_free_tools_for_data_visualization_and_analysis&quot;&gt;30 free dataviz tools&lt;/a&gt;.	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A favorite for making embeddable maps and charts, Google’s experimental &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/fusiontables/&quot;&gt;Fusion Tables&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2012/12/talking-data-in-the-nutmeg-state.html&quot;&gt;Fusion Tables tutorial&lt;/a&gt; (on the second half of the post).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://support.google.com/fusiontables/answer/184641/?hl=en&amp;amp;&quot;&gt;More Fusion Tables tutorials&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9215504/22_free_tools_for_data_visualization_and_analysis?pageNumber=4#tableau&quot;&gt;Tableau Public&lt;/a&gt;, another free data viz program.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://datawrapper.de/&quot;&gt;DataWrapper&lt;/a&gt;, more free charts, powered by your Google Spreadsheet&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Google’s new, free &lt;a href=&quot;http://google-latlong.blogspot.com/2013/03/create-collaborate-and-share-advanced.html&quot;&gt;Map Engine Lite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make searchable, sortable tables and embed them with &lt;a href=&quot;http://multimedia.journalism.berkeley.edu/tools/freedive/&quot;&gt;FreeDive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interaction&quot;&gt;5. Interaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hackjersey&quot;&gt;open source code from Hack Jersey&lt;/a&gt; on Github. (Remember the caveat that this is hackathon code and in most cases probably not ready for prime time)	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;http://source.mozillaopennews.org/en-US/&quot;&gt;Source blog&lt;/a&gt; from Knight-Mozilla &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mozillaopennews.org/&quot;&gt;Open News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;support-groups&quot;&gt;Support groups&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ire.org/&quot;&gt;Investigative Reporters &amp;amp; Editors&lt;/a&gt;	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ire.org/resource-center/listservs/subscribe-nicar-l/&quot;&gt;IRE’s NICAR-L email list &lt;/a&gt;for computer-assisted reporting and data journalism discussion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hackshackers.com/&quot;&gt;Hacks/Hackers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://journalists.org/&quot;&gt;Online News Association&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And for more advanced topics, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chryswu.com/blog/2013/02/27/tools-slides-links-tutorials-nicar13/&quot;&gt;Chrys Wu’s blog posts&lt;/a&gt; rounding up all the tools, classes and workshops at IRE’s CAR conference are must-reads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are your favorite data techniques, tools and tutorials? Please share them with me. I’d love to check them out.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/04/diving-in-to-data-with-spj.html&quot;&gt;Diving into data with SPJ&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on April 12, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I learned organizing a hackathon]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/04/organizing-my-first-hackathon.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/04/organizing-my-first-hackathon</id>
  <published>2013-04-04T11:08:14-04:00</published>
  <updated>2013-04-04T11:08:14-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It all started in September, at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ona12.journalists.org/&quot;&gt;Online News Association&lt;/a&gt;’s conference in San Francisco. I crashed the &lt;a href=&quot;http://wjchat.webjournalist.org/&quot;&gt;#wjchat&lt;/a&gt; party and ended up meeting the infamous &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.debragalant.com/&quot;&gt;Debbie Galant&lt;/a&gt;, the force of nature behind &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.baristanet.com/&quot;&gt;Baristanet&lt;/a&gt; who was just starting the &lt;a href=&quot;http://njnewscommons.org/&quot;&gt;NJ News Commons&lt;/a&gt;. We talked about journalism in Jersey. I floated the idea of a news hackathon, and she was intrigued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward through a hurricane, an election, months of planning and promotion, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/2013/03/11/rounding-up-our-hack-weekend/&quot;&gt;24 hours of hacking&lt;/a&gt;. I sat in a lecture hall at Montclair State University listening in awe to 11 teams of journalists and programmers pitch their projects to change news in New Jersey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I’m glossing over many logistical details here. I’ll just say that we could not have pulled it off without the generosity and advice of our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/sponsors-2/&quot;&gt;sponsors and partners&lt;/a&gt;, especially the News Commons and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.montclair.edu/arts/school-of-communication-and-media/&quot;&gt;the university&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mozillaopennews.org/&quot;&gt;Knight-Mozilla OpenNews&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cartodb.com/&quot;&gt;CartoDB&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.oreilly.com/&quot;&gt;O’Reilly&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nj.com/&quot;&gt;The Star-Ledger&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.northjersey.com/&quot;&gt;The Record&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patch.com/&quot;&gt;Patch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://echolocation.com/&quot;&gt;Echo&lt;/a&gt; and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t believe we pulled it off. There’s no way I could have imagined in September how much I’d learn about building community, blending cultures and sowing the seeds for us to think about news and data in new ways. Among those lessons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It was a serious miscalculation on my part to try to start at 9 a.m. on a Saturday. Neither journalists nor developers are early risers. As we waited for folks to drift in, we had to start late and rush some of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/2013/03/11/rounding-up-our-hack-weekend/&quot;&gt;the presentations&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One of the biggest challenges was trying to manage people’s expectations of what they’d get out of giving up a weekend to stare at a computer screen on a college campus. Some people wanted to learn to code. Others wanted nerds to help them with their next big project. A few, I imagine, wanted to network for a job. We wanted everyone to feel like she or he could be a part of this experience and could offer something, no matter previous experience or skill level. For some newsroom denizens whose only exposure to developers was their much maligned IT staff, this was a revolutionary idea. They have been trained to treat technologists like a deli counter: Order up whatever newfangled internet thing you need and wait for it to show up. My hope was at the end of the hackathon, our reporters and developers could start to imagine how they can work together. I think on that front we succeeded.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We may have overloaded the schedule with speakers, and our talks were geared too heavily toward journalists. Some of the participants would have liked more discussion of the process of creating news apps rather than the concepts of data journalism and news app thinking. Others wanted less yakking and more hacking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s just as important for us to bring programmers to the news world as it is to introduce journalists to the development process. We succeeded on the latter, but we need to do more for the former. We could have used speakers from the tech world who would have lured more programmers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I wish we had more diversity in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/speakers/&quot;&gt;our roster of speakers&lt;/a&gt;. I was thrilled to have Emily Bell as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/judges/&quot;&gt;one of our judges&lt;/a&gt;. A majority of the folks on our planning committee were women, as were many of our participants. But I think we erred in not having more women presenters, giving a false impression of the state of news development and the programming world as a whole.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We just didn’t have enough developers. We needed to have more than one on each team, preferably someone with backend skills and someone else with frontend skills. Some of the teams had one developer and four journalists. That just didn’t work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We found some teams didn’t need more than one or two journalists, even those with significant computer-assisted reporting skills. Some of the CAR veterans had a hard time translating their expertise in analyzing data to the idea of developing a reusable application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To my surprise, many of the programmers were not really familiar &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.tommeagher.com/2013/03/learning-to-commit-to-version-control/&quot;&gt;with version control or git&lt;/a&gt;. Only Sunday morning, as the deadline loomed, did some teams ask about how to use Github, leaving me to run around and teach people. Some teams also didn’t have server space to host a demo site, something I assumed was a given. A suggestion from judge and mentor Jonathan Soo was to have us offer hosted server space for the teams and to require everyone to push an initial commit to Github within the first hour of hacking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The teams with strong projects at the end either came with an idea or settled on one very quickly. We need a mechanism for teams to find members and for people to think about data and project ideas ahead of time. Some teams spent far too much time arguing over ideas or failed to really evaluate the data they were hoping to use. Suggestions were made for a pre-networking event a week before or a forum or email list for people to talk ahead of time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I realized far too late that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/&quot;&gt;our website&lt;/a&gt; was good for displaying details on the event planning, but &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/blog-2/&quot;&gt;the blog&lt;/a&gt; was completely unusable. The commenting system didn’t work at all. Next time, we need to test that earlier or set up a functional blog at blog.hackjersey.com.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hackjersey&quot;&gt;our 11 projects&lt;/a&gt;, three teams didn’t finish enough to present anything beyond what they learned from not finishing. Another four teams had very rough demos, but had proofs of concept to show. So &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/2013/01/28/and-the-winners-are/&quot;&gt;four teams finished&lt;/a&gt; pretty much functional projects.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to build a strong community, the best way to start is by recruiting a broad coalition of journalists, developers, designers, hackers, educators, nonprofits and bureaucrats to help plan the event. Thanks in large part to Debbie Galant, we had more than 20 people on our organizing committee, and their ideas and dedication made this hackathon work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I considered our first Hack Jersey event a success. And that leads us to think about what’s next. We have a few ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An ongoing sponsorship from the New Jersey News Commons and the School of Communication and Media at Montclair State University.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A hack day aimed at scraping a poorly structured public dataset that could be hosted for all to use freely.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Programming training, perhaps through a partnership with other groups who have already invented that wheel.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Basic data reporting training, which many working journalists say they are hungry for.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Solicit ideas for newsroom tools from news organizations large and small. Take that list of use cases and host a hack day or series of hack days to build open source tools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hackjersey.com/&quot;&gt;Hack Jersey&lt;/a&gt; should work on next? What would be most useful to you as a journalist? If you’re a developer, what kind of projects would you be interested in working on with us? I’d love to hear your ideas. Please share them in the comments, or email us at hackinfo(at)hackjersey(dot)com.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/04/organizing-my-first-hackathon.html&quot;&gt;What I learned organizing a hackathon&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on April 04, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning to commit to version control]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/02/learning-to-commit-to-version-control.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/02/learning-to-commit-to-version-control</id>
  <published>2013-02-28T23:33:24-05:00</published>
  <updated>2013-02-28T23:33:24-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At this week’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ire.org/conferences/nicar-2013/&quot;&gt;computer-assisted reporting conference&lt;/a&gt; in Louisville, IRE has me doing double-duty. In addition to my class on &lt;a href=&quot;bit.ly/car13refine&quot;&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/a&gt;, I’m also teaching a hands-on session on &lt;a href=&quot;http://git-scm.com/&quot;&gt;git&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assumes you’ve already &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/set-up-git&quot;&gt;downloaded git&lt;/a&gt; and created an account on Github. I use the command line, although if you master that, the GUI clients will be a piece of cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve somehow, inadvertently become a bit of a Git evangelist, not out of any mastery, but mostly because of my convert’s zeal for version control.  And the one-two punch of git and Github have changed the way I think about my job, web development and sharing knowledge. Here’s a quick run-through of the class. If you’re a visual learner, the slides are here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/car13gitslides&quot;&gt;http://bit.ly/car13gitslides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-git&quot;&gt;What is git?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distributed_version_control_system&quot;&gt;distributed version control system&lt;/a&gt; (If this doesn’t mean anything to you, don’t sweat it. It’s mostly for the nerds)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;a command line utility to track changes to a file and to share those changes with others.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;good for any kind of text - stories, csv, html, .js, .py, .rb.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;not so great with images, audio, video&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-git-do&quot;&gt;What does git do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a broad oversimplification, it uses &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diff&quot;&gt;diff&lt;/a&gt; to compare every addition and subtraction in your code and shows you how your files evolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It lets you take snapshots of your code and roll through them over time (or back in time) as needed to follow how a file changes from save to save to save. And you can have several authors of a file branch off their own versions to edit and then later merge them all back together into one master file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.clasesdeperiodismo.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/06/Newsdiff-mubarak.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of things going on behind the curtain in git, that you can figure out eventually, but don’t worry about it here. For right now, basically you only need to really know six commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you want to know is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will orient you to where you are, what files have changed and whether you’ve saved your snapshot of your project (which we’ll soon start calling a “commit”). This is your friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where you work and where you edit your code is the working directory. When you’re ready to take a snapshot of your code, you “add” your file to the staging area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git add foo.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://codingdomain.com/git/partial-commits/git-staging-area.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you’ve made all the changes you want, and you’ve “added” all of your updated files to the staging area, it’s time to make a commit. And with each commit, you want to add a short message describing what the changes are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git commit -m &amp;quot;finally debugged my own idiocy. maybe...&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now all of your updates are saved in your file respository, and if you want to, you can your snapshot is made. You could very easily stop here and just keep the audit trail on your machine. But the other half of this happy marriage is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com&quot;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-github&quot;&gt;What is Github?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/kinlane-productions/api-evangelist/github/github-logo-transparent.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Github is a social coding site, and it’s a hosted remote repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It lets you back up all of your code online (for free if it’s open source), and it lets you see how other developers do it and learn from their work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how you do it: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git push -u origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You “push” your code from the “master” branch that’s on your machine to your remote repository on Github, which we call “origin.” (This may have already been configured for you if you cloned your repo from github. Otherwise, you would have to &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git remote add origin git@github.com:tommeagher/myrepo.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the many great things about Github is that you can see the diff in your files without the Matrix hypnosis of command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last couple commands I’ll tell you are how you get your commits from the remote repository on Github back on your machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git fetch origin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to gather the updated files from your remote “origin” repository. Now you want to “merge” the changes from the master branch on your remote “origin” repository into your master branch on your machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;git merge origin/master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now your files are updated from the remote repository. Now keep coding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want more, you can visit the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com/tommeagher/gitintro&quot;&gt;repo for this class&lt;/a&gt;, where I have a cheat sheet for the most common basic uses and commands and more in-depth tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This really just deals with the basics. We haven’t even had a chance to talk about &lt;a href=&quot;http://githowto.com/resolving_conflicts&quot;&gt;merge problems&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gitref.org/branching/&quot;&gt;branching&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.github.com/articles/fork-a-repo&quot;&gt;forking &lt;/a&gt;or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www-cs-students.stanford.edu/~blynn/gitmagic/ch03.html&quot;&gt;cloning&lt;/a&gt;, but you know how to Google, so you can figure it out. Fork my repo, improve the cheat sheet and send me a pull request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s your favorite tip or cheat in git? Leave me a comment. I’d love to read it.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/02/learning-to-commit-to-version-control.html&quot;&gt;Learning to commit to version control&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on February 28, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[More tips for using OpenRefine]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/02/more-tips-for-using-openrefine.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/02/more-tips-for-using-openrefine</id>
  <published>2013-02-26T22:37:54-05:00</published>
  <updated>2013-02-26T22:37:54-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;At IRE’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ire.org/conferences/nicar-2013/&quot;&gt;computer-assisted reporting conference&lt;/a&gt; this week in Louisville, I am once again teaching a course on using &lt;a href=&quot;http://openrefine.org/&quot;&gt;OpenRefine&lt;/a&gt; to clean data. Although the program has changed names over the last few months, its features are pretty much the same, and it’s still an amazingly powerful and free tool for cleaning and standardizing difficult data. If you ever find yourself frustrated with typos, misspellings or any number of other mistakes in the data you get from government agencies, OpenRefine will change your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won’t repeat verbatim my Refine tutorial, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2012/06/clean-data-is-the-best-weapon-against-the-planet-of-the-apes.html&quot;&gt;which you can find here&lt;/a&gt;, but I will share some of the resources again and point you to a few other tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, check out the updated &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/car13refineslides&quot;&gt;slides for my class&lt;/a&gt;. If you’d like to follow along with the class, you can download our data for the &lt;a href=&quot;/files/data/lotterywinners.csv&quot;&gt;lottery winners&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;/files/data/nj-hospital-2012.xls&quot;&gt;hospital report cards&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;/files/data/nassau_police_union_contribs.xls&quot;&gt;campaign finance data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re just looking for a good cheat sheet of Refine’s key functions, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/car13refinecheats&quot;&gt;try this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you thought my class was easy, and you’re looking for more help with Refine, I can recommend these tutorials, from Refine creator &lt;a href=&quot;http://davidhuynh.net/spaces/nicar2011/tutorial.pdf&quot;&gt;David Huynh&lt;/a&gt;, developer &lt;a href=&quot;http://dannguyen.github.com/NICAR-Google-Refine/&quot;&gt;Dan Nguyen&lt;/a&gt; and journalism educator &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinejournalismblog.com/2011/07/05/cleaning-data-using-google-refine-a-quick-guide/&quot;&gt;Paul Bradshaw&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s your favorite use for OpenRefine? Leave a comment here, drop me an email or mention me on Twitter. I’d love to hear what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2013/02/more-tips-for-using-openrefine.html&quot;&gt;More tips for using OpenRefine&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on February 26, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talking data in the Nutmeg State]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/12/talking-data-in-the-nutmeg-state.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/12/talking-data-in-the-nutmeg-state</id>
  <published>2012-12-11T12:08:02-05:00</published>
  <updated>2012-12-11T12:08:02-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update: In mid-December, I led two days of training in data journalism techniques for my colleagues at the New Haven Register. On a Thursday evening, I took the Amtrak train home to New Jersey, feeling good about turning a group of journalists on to the power and fun of incorporating data into their reporting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The next morning, the horrible shooting at Newtown Elementary School threw our world upside-down. Only now, more than two months later, have I been able to take a moment to revisit the rough notes and links I dumped here in December to try to make them a little more useful.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The first class was an overview discussion of “data journalism” and the many and sundry techniques that encompasses. The second class was a hands-on walk-through of Excel and Google Fusion Tables. The handouts and cheatsheets cover nearly all of the tips we discussed. If you have questions, or would like to know more, please leave a comment or send me an email.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro-to-data---slide-deckhttpwwwhaikudeckcompsd9nvkcej0&quot;&gt;Intro to data -&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.haikudeck.com/p/sd9NVKceJ0&quot;&gt; slide deck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;handouts&quot;&gt;Handouts:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/tips/mathhandout.doc&quot;&gt;Newsroom math overview&lt;/a&gt;	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/tips/NumbersintheNewsroom.doc&quot;&gt;Numbers in the Newsroom by Sarah Cohen&lt;/a&gt; by Sarah Cohen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/tips/NewsroomMathCribSheet.doc&quot;&gt;Newsroom math crib sheet by Steve Doig&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;extra-reading&quot;&gt;Extra reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sampler.isr.umich.edu/2011/featured/revealing-the-roots-of-a-riot/&quot;&gt;The roots of “precision journalism”&lt;/a&gt;	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.santacruzlive.com/blogs/online/2012/11/27/how-sentinel-reporter-jason-hoppin-predicted-the-outcome-of-local-supervisors-race/&quot;&gt;How Jason Hoppin predicted a close local election&lt;/a&gt;	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A video of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.palewire.com&quot;&gt;Ben Welsh&lt;/a&gt;’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/iP-On8PzEy8&quot;&gt;talk on data journalism&lt;/a&gt;. He explains it very well, ”It’s only in journalism that we continue to distinguish ourselves with the use of Microsoft Excel.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hands-on-excel--fusion-tables-class&quot;&gt;Hands-on Excel &amp;amp; Fusion Tables class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;data-for-excel-exercises&quot;&gt;Data for Excel exercises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/2012/11/schoolsdatav1.xlsx&quot;&gt;Schoolsdatav1.xlsx&lt;/a&gt;	&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/2012/11/2010-2011hs-prresults.xlsx&quot;&gt;2010-2011hs-prresults.xlsx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/2012/11/demographicsnapshot2012public.xlsx&quot;&gt;DemographicSnapshotEdited.xlsx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/2008/09/3appointmentsclass.xls&quot;&gt;Appointments.xls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/2008/09/8crony.xls&quot;&gt;Crony.xls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/2008/09/10citybud.xls&quot;&gt;citybud.xls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s do something fun and map the data for a story, using Google’s experimental (and free) &lt;a href=&quot;http://tables.googlelabs.com/&quot;&gt;Fusion Tables&lt;/a&gt; program. We’re going to download a spreadsheet in the CSV format of the violent crime rates for every town in Connecticut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.datahaven.org&quot;&gt;DataHaven.org&lt;/a&gt; Go to indicators&amp;gt;Public safety&amp;gt;Community safety&amp;gt;Violent crimes&amp;gt; total violent crime rate
Select all towns and hit the submit button. Click “All years” and hit submit again. Now you can download the CSV, which stands for comma-separated values. It’s essentially a spreadsheet without any of the fancy highlighting or formatting of Excel. It’s a universal format, and when given the option, it’s a good idea to get your data in CSV. Because of its simple structure, it’s easy for a human to read and just about any computer can understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we have our data, but if we want to visualize it, we need a map to put it on. We can get this map from a SHP (pronounced “shape”) file.  Luckily, in many states, the government or academic institutions often have a clearing house for this kind of geographic data. In Connecticut, you can find it at the U. Conn. library. Point your browser toward &lt;a href=&quot;http://magic.lib.uconn.edu/&quot;&gt;http://magic.lib.uconn.edu/&lt;/a&gt;, then look under the “CT GIS” column and click on the “&lt;a href=&quot;http://magic.lib.uconn.edu/connecticut_data.html#boundaries&quot;&gt;Boundaries&lt;/a&gt;” section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grab the “Connecticut Towns” shapefile from 2010. Then you have to convert the file to a format that Fusion Tables can use. Luckily, there is a free website called “&lt;a href=&quot;http://shpescape.com/&quot;&gt;Shp Escape&lt;/a&gt;” that can help. Give it your shp file and log into your Google account and it will automatically transform the file and ship it into your Fusion Tables account. Some times the site can be a little busy, so it may take a few minutes. Be patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, that you have your map file in Fusion Tables, you need the data you want to visualize. Go to Google Drive, click the “create” button and choose Fusion Table. Choose the “download.csv” file that you got from Data Haven and put this into your Fusion Table. (Notice, Fusion Tables also allows you to import tabular data directly from a Google Spreadsheeet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clean up the column headings in the file to make the more meaningful. Now we’re going to merge the data file back to the shape file we already uploaded. Under the “File” dropdown menu, choose “Merge.” Find your Connecticut Towns shape table. And you have to determine which field to join the tables on. What field is the same in both tables? Notice that the “town” field in the crime table matches the “NAME10” field in the shape file. That’s your key to join the tables together. Just be certain that each town name only appears once in that column in each table (in this example, it does).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it sends you into Fusion Tables, click the “About this table” link under the File dropdown menu and “edit table information.” Update the name of the table, give it a meaningful description, attribution and a link to the original download. This can help you later to retrace your steps and bulletproof your reporting. It will also help others who look at your work and want to see your primary source material. Click on the “Share” button and make the map public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have both tables combined together into one, new, merged table. But if you click on the “Map” tab, it probably still doesn’t look right. We need to style the representation of the data. While you’re on the map tab, go to the “Tools” dropdown and click on “Change Map Styles.” This will allow us to choose how we want to color code the towns based on their crime rate. Instead of points, we want to click on “Fill color” under the “Polygons” section. Points would be if we were color-coding pins on individual addresses. Instead, we want to shade an entire town based on its crime rate, thus we want “polygon.” For the fill color, let’s pick the “buckets” tab, which means we can choose four different colors to represent the range of crime rates in our area. If you want to fancy, you can choose whatever color you want for each bucket. Hit the “save” button. Are all of your towns filled in with a color? (You can ignore the “&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cslib.org/jog.htm&quot;&gt;Southwick Jog&lt;/a&gt;”). If not, then you probably haven’t set the range of values for your crime rate to the include all of them. Adjust the high and low ends of your range until none of your towns are blank. This may take some jiggering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Play with the bucket sizes and colors of the buckets. What makes sense? Is everything in there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the title to change the attribution and background info for the merged table. Share the merged table and make it public. Then click Tools&amp;gt; Publish. This gives you the embed code for you to put it in your story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you get the hang of this, you can but producing web-ready interactive maps in 20-30 minutes, a task that would have taken hours or days not all that long ago. This is an awesome tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.google.com/fusiontables/embedviz?viz=MAP&amp;amp;q=select+col0%3E%3E1+from+1hJY9IspBzWrEx5csZTISYn_r4JKlbTBIlGZyyyI&amp;amp;h=false&amp;amp;lat=41.620240308269935&amp;amp;lng=-72.47735563281253&amp;amp;z=8&amp;amp;t=1&amp;amp;l=col0%3E%3E1&amp;amp;y=2&amp;amp;tmplt=2&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few more things that you can tweak, if you like. You can go to Tools&amp;gt;Change info window layout, to tweak the information that’s displayed when you click on a polygon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And one last tip, you don’t always have to upload your own data or map files. You can go to Help&amp;gt;Search Public Tables and browse through all of the data that other Fusion Tables users have uploaded. Of course, as with all reporting, the caveat is to mindful of the source. Always confirm the information and data with other parties. But if you find a good shapefile, you could use it again and again. It’s definitely worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the super fast and dirty introduction to Fusion Tables. Now, go explore it some more on your own. What’s your favorite trick in Fusion Tables? Drop me an email, leave a comment or mention me on Twitter and I’ll add it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tipsheets and tutorials&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/tips/xlgetaround.doc&quot;&gt;Getting around Excel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/tips/xlsort.doc&quot;&gt;Sorting in Excel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/tips/xlpowerformula.doc&quot;&gt;Power formulas in Excel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://businessjournalism.org/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/xlpivot_updated.pdf&quot;&gt;Excel filters and pivot tables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://support.google.com/fusiontables/answer/184641/?hl=en&amp;amp;&quot;&gt;More Fusion Tables tutorials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/fusiontablestalks/stories&quot;&gt;Examples of cool uses of Fusion Tables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/12/talking-data-in-the-nutmeg-state.html&quot;&gt;Talking data in the Nutmeg State&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on December 11, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not another blinking PDF!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/08/pdfs.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/08/pdfs</id>
  <published>2012-08-05T06:50:40-04:00</published>
  <updated>2012-08-05T06:50:40-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are few things more frustrating than trying to get a simple spreadsheet from a government agency and being told by a spokesman that the data (say, a table of property tax rates in municipalities that was clearly created in Excel) only exists in a locked PDF format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of expediency, you sometimes just have to bite the bullet and try to wrestle the data free from the PDF’s clutches so that you can gently guide it into a more useful spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not always easy, but here are a few resources to do just that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Nguyen at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.propublica.org/&quot;&gt;ProPublica&lt;/a&gt; crafted this very helpful and comprehensive &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.propublica.org/nerds/item/turning-pdfs-to-text-doc-dollars-guide&quot;&gt;guide to the various strategies for unlocking data from PDFs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also had some success using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cometdocs.com/&quot;&gt;CometDocs&lt;/a&gt;, a free site that had a surprisingly high accuracy rate for converting documents on one particularly labor-intensive project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not afraid of installing a simple command line program, I’ve also had some luck with PDF2text. Here’s a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ire.org/resourcecenter/nettour/PDFTOTEXT.pdf&quot;&gt;nice tutorial from IRE&lt;/a&gt; (looks like the link may be temporarily broken), as well as a guide to how to &lt;a href=&quot;http://ire.org/blog/on-the-road/2010/09/01/quick-fix-to-tame-pdfs/&quot;&gt;automate the conversions&lt;/a&gt; and not be bothered by the pesky command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve heard good things about the commercial software &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docudesk.com/deskpdf/pdf-converter&quot;&gt;DeskUnPDF&lt;/a&gt;, but I haven’t had an opportunity to use it myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you don’t have the time or patience to negotiate with an agency to give you what you want how you want it, give these solutions a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have other techniques for culling data from PDFs, please share them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/08/pdfs.html&quot;&gt;Not another blinking PDF!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on August 05, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to get a head count at the parade]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/07/crowd-estimates.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/07/crowd-estimates</id>
  <published>2012-07-28T12:01:01-04:00</published>
  <updated>2012-07-28T12:01:01-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is another in the series of “Best Practices” posts from my archives from the Herald News. This was also written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/2008/02/maslow-mourned/&quot;&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/a&gt;, and offers some solid street reporting tips for counting the crowd at any large public event.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;News reporting often involves telling how many people took part in or attended an event. Sometimes the seating capacity is known, as in the case of a sports stadium. Sometimes an official estimates the crowd size, sometimes the organizers estimate. Sometimes they don’t agree. Sometimes no one estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good practice for the reporter to do his or her own estimation in all cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For inside events, a quick head count with a qualifying “about” is good. (“about 75 people attended the planning board session.”) The tried and true method of estimating crowd size is as follows:
1) make a careful measurement of the area in which the event takes place. Simply put, that’s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;length times width equals square feet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In some cases, it may take a slightly more sophisticated algorithm (the crowd covers the sidewalks on six blocks. Ask officials how long each block is, walk off the width of sidewalk. Multiply).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Decide whether it’s a dense crowd or a loose crowd. People packed into a subway car, for example, are a dense crowd and occupy 2 square feet per person. A loose crowd, such as a parade of journalists on May Day, has one person per five square feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Divide the area by the crowd density, and you’ve got your estimated crowd.
Example: A political rally takes place in the square outside City Hall. You pace it off and find it’s 150 feet long and 100 feet wide, or 15,000 square feet. You wade into the crowd to test the density. Some places toward the front are packed, but in the back it’s loose. You choose a density in between of one person per three square feet. Divide 15,000 by 3 = 5,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;area: 150 x 100 = 15,000
estimate of density: 3 sq. feet/per person
15,000 divided by 3 = 5,000 attendees&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If AP is covering an event, check your estimate against theirs, which is based on aerial/satellite photography and should be accurate. If yours and theirs are at great odds, dig in your heels and insist the wire services are an ass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: [Then] Passaic County Sherriff’s communications man Bill Maer says the county uses a slight variation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;1) Count how many people are actually in a 10 x 10 foot area (that’s 100 square feet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Measure on foot or get a good estimate of the size of the entire area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) divide the total area by 100 (the number of 10 by 10 squares)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Multiply the result by how many people are in the sample 10 x 10 foot square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I think this adds an unnecessary step, but it does make the reckoning of density a bit more accurate and hence, perhaps, the crowd estimate itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/em&gt;, Herald News, Nov. 2003&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/07/crowd-estimates.html&quot;&gt;How to get a head count at the parade&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on July 28, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nerds need credit too]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/07/nerds-need-credit-too.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/07/nerds-need-credit-too</id>
  <published>2012-07-21T22:57:56-04:00</published>
  <updated>2012-07-21T22:57:56-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seems odd in 2012 that in some newsrooms the data journalists don’t get the same kind of credit for their work that other reporters receive. I suppose it’s understandable, if NICAR-L is any indication, because to some of our colleagues data work is a mysterious and opaque contribution to a story and thus they don’t quite know how or when to give us a byline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the policy we used when I was the CAR reporter at the Herald News, and it was heavily modeled (in some parts verbatim) on the one adopted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/gebeloffnyt/&quot;&gt;Rob Gebeloff&lt;/a&gt;, then of The Star-Ledger and now at the New York Times. This slightly updated policy also guides us today at The Star-Ledger as we decide when our work merits a byline. It’s a good place for newsrooms to start the conversation about the work of their data people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The data journalist is available every day for assistance, large and small, on daily, breaking and enterprise stories. The reporter is here to help locate data. When another reporter or editor asks for a quick fact here or there (such as a basic Census figure), no credit is necessary. It’s part of the job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many times, the quick fact search turns into an analysis of data. When this analysis produces “proprietary information” that supports a story, the data journalist should receive a tagline on the story. For example, a colleague wants a complete breakdown of Census data for a particular neighborhood—a task that would require the reporter to assemble the data piecemeal from several tables or sources—this would create proprietary information unique to our news gathering. If this information is even just a few paragraphs of the story, a tagline is appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the data journalist does a significant analysis of data that creates proprietary information that becomes the thesis of a story, he or she will receive a byline. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Even if the data journalist does not write another word in the published piece, his or her reporting forms the basis of a story and thus warrants a byline.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the journalist analyzes a new set of data released by a government agency and finds that homeowners in suburban Passaic County are scooping up flood insurance hand over fist. The reporter assembles the analyzed data and passes it on to the real estate reporter who finds additional sources for quotes and writes the story. The nut graf of the story should say “a Herald News analysis of TK data has found…” and the data journalist shares the byline with the other reporter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Tom Meagher, Herald News, July 2006, via Rob Gebeloff at The Star-Ledger&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/07/nerds-need-credit-too.html&quot;&gt;Nerds need credit too&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on July 21, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Waking from an election results nightmare]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/waking-from-the-election-results-nightmare.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/waking-from-the-election-results-nightmare</id>
  <published>2012-06-30T23:14:53-04:00</published>
  <updated>2012-06-30T23:14:53-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, especially after a particularly trying election night, it starts to feel like we may be suffering from post-polls PTSD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past year and a half, we’ve been experimenting at The Star-Ledger with ways to improve how we report election results online and in print. In many elections, we’ll have hundreds of races spread across a dozen counties. And none of the officials overseeing those elections provides a useful electronic feed of results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve tried off-the-shelf products to input election data into tables with disastrous, near-comical results. Without a single developer in our newsroom, we’ve cobbled together solutions and written hundreds of lines of code to reverse engineer our hand-collected data and take it from our website into our print pagination system. For something that’s over in just a few hours, we invest an incredible amount of time and effort into getting it right, often without being really satisfied with the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of that struggle has led us here, to our proposal for the Knight Foundation’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newschallenge.org&quot;&gt;News Innovation Challenge&lt;/a&gt; for a &lt;a href=&quot;http://tommeagher.tumblr.com/post/25573223080/knight-news-challenge-round-2-voter-the-versatile&quot;&gt;project we’re calling VOTER&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VOTER is a browser-based program that will help organizations streamline the collection of election results and create embeddable online graphics that will work on any website, especially the common blogging platforms that power many news operations. It is still very early in the development process, but we’re excited about the News Challenge and even more psyched about the possibility that we can turn our trauma into something that will save newsrooms everywhere a whole lot of heartache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? We’d love to hear your experiences, both good and bad, from the election nights you’ve covered. What’s worked for you to get results online and what hasn’t? Leave a comment here or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/ultracasual&quot;&gt;tweet at me&lt;/a&gt;. And, most importantly, tell us what VOTER will need to do to make it useful for your organization.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/waking-from-the-election-results-nightmare.html&quot;&gt;Waking from an election results nightmare&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on June 30, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bolstering transparency in our reporting]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/transparency.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/transparency</id>
  <published>2012-06-24T11:55:45-04:00</published>
  <updated>2012-06-24T11:55:45-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back at the Herald News, several of the editors and reporters wrote a regular series of columns for the newsroom called “Best Practices.” In digging through my archives, I’ve found several that are timeless that I will gradually repost. This first one was written by &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2008/02/maslow-mourned.html&quot;&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/a&gt;, and his tips for being transparent in our reporting and writing continue to ring true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our credibility as journalists and as a newspaper is the most important equity we have in the marketplace of ideas. The more readers trust us, the better our performance. We have to earn that trust every single day. One of the most important ways to do this is leveling with our readers: telling them what we know, how we know it, what we don’t know, why we don’t know it and what’s what. In practice this entails the highest degree of transparency possible in our publication. Work toward greater transparency: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Don’t use hearsay. Don’t describe things you didn’t see, but rather attribute it to a firsthand witness and tell the reader who that witness was. If you are writing about a public meeting you did not attend, be aware that readers must not be given a false impression. You don’t need to say you weren’t there. But you can’t report things as if you were there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Don’t just use the boilerplate “sources said,” but give the reader as much information as you can without breaching trust, for example: “two sources in the AG’s office familiar with the case,” or “a high official in the department who asked her name not be used because she feared political retribution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Don’t just use the cliche “the mayor could not be reached for comment.” Use instead: “the mayor did not return repeated phone calls for comment over a three-day period, although City Hall said he was not on vacation or out of town on business.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) As you know, we sometimes have problems getting information from police on weekends. Don’t just let this go with “police did not release information.” Tell the readers, e.g., “Sgt. Troy Anthony said he could not release any information about the incident, because Mayor Sammy Torres, who is also acting public safety director, has told the police department that all news releases must go through his office. The mayor did not return five phone calls Sunday.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transparency is a habit, a muscle. Flex it and it gets stronger. And your work gets more accurate, better, more useful to readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/em&gt;, Herald News, June, 2004&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/transparency.html&quot;&gt;Bolstering transparency in our reporting&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on June 24, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clean data is the best weapon against the monkey insurrection]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/clean-data-is-the-best-weapon-against-the-planet-of-the-apes.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/clean-data-is-the-best-weapon-against-the-planet-of-the-apes</id>
  <published>2012-06-15T00:06:43-04:00</published>
  <updated>2012-06-15T00:06:43-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Updated:&lt;/strong&gt; I added the link to the rough cheat sheet of handy and common Refine tasks at &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/ire12refinecheats&quot;&gt;http://bit.ly/ire12refinecheats&lt;/a&gt;. Send me your favorite tricks to add to the list!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a rough walkthrough of the class I’m teaching at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ire.org/conferences/ire-2012/&quot;&gt;2012 IRE conference&lt;/a&gt; in Boston on how to use Google Refine to clean data. If you’d like to see them, these are the slides from the session, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bit.ly/ire12refineslides&quot;&gt;http://bit.ly/ire12refineslides&lt;/a&gt;. Please forgive the weird line returns of WordPress. If you hit any hiccups or have suggestions for improvement, please leave a comment or mention me on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/ultracasual&quot;&gt;@ultracasual&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;youre-faced-with-a-dilemma-thats-fairly-common-in-many-newsrooms&quot;&gt;You’re faced with a dilemma that’s fairly common in many newsrooms.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Say, for example, a series of accidents kills a number of children crossing busy streets near you. Now, you want to know the deadliest roads or intersections in your area (this is not the dilemma, just wait for it). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_f0bvyZMrZ9k/TTjrIgdvMaI/AAAAAAAAGFE/UppLYR8YaJw/s1600/barney-fife.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always say in the news business to check it out, and we shouldn’t trust anecdote and the frailty of human memory.  So where do you go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this guy, right, look like he has an encyclopedic knowledge of every fatal accident in your five-county coverage area?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;File a public records request and get the data. It should have the answer you need, right? You pick up your CD with the data, or if you’re really lucky, the state police will have a file you can download from their website. You expect to get a tidy Excel spreadsheet with very orderly numbers on it. Everything will be geocoded, and you’ll just need to do one quick pivot table or one quick group-by query and drop it into &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/fusiontables/Home/&quot;&gt;Fusion Tables&lt;/a&gt; and BAM! you’re done with your story. It writes itself, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.cartoonstock.com/newscartoons/cartoonists/mbc/lowres/mbcn1960l.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You laugh, but this is what I spent years believing, and every time I was–and continue to be–flabbergasted by the sloppiness of the public data I get my hands on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I worked on the dangerous intersections story, I got something that looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/refine.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;refine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This is a dramatization)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As David Donald said in his CAR panel yesterday, cleaning is the longest and hardest part of the data process. Assume any data you get is dirty and full of holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Government data is hardly unique in this respect, but it is our bread and butter, and frankly we should expect better from the government, so I’ll pick on it today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-so-much-public-data-such-a-mess&quot;&gt;Why is so much public data such a mess?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Much like journalists, government agencies are not nearly as good with numbers as they ought to be.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When databases exist, they are often built on things never intended to be turned into relational data, like hand-written accident reports.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many agencies seem to subscribe to the&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infinite_monkey_theorem&quot;&gt; infinite monkey theorem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.demandstudiossucks.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/monkey-typewriter-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone unfamiliar with it, the infinite monkey theorem more or less says that given an infinite amount of time and an infinite number of monkeys with typewriters, eventually the monkeys will write the complete works of Shakespeare or “A Tale of Two Cities.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you work with a lot of public data, this is what feels like. Occasionally there’s something correct, but before you find it, you have to wade through what seems like a near-infinite number of errors.  I’m not suggesting that government employees are primates, but I am pretty certain that they’re outsourcing their data entry to monkeys… and it gets worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because these monkeys are not geniuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://images.wikia.com/planetoftheapes/images/a/a3/Zaius_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are enemies of good data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These monkeys are mean, and they hate puppies and clean data (and water). To be fair, in my completely unscientific survey, the data has gotten better in the past decade, but it’s not where it should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every data entry mistake possible will be made. Often you fill find new mistakes that you never, ever would have considered or imagined in your wildest dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These clerical errors will make your life miserable. You can either welcome our new monkey overlords or you can arm yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-old-tools&quot;&gt;The old tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Excel: filters, pivot tables, string functions&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Access: Group by queries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Notepad++: Regular expressions&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Scripting language for automated, repetitive cleaning&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these, the cleaning of the database could take days or weeks or longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can do it with Google Refine in a few hours or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/76/Google-refine-logo.svg/631px-Google-refine-logo.svg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can take that crap and turn it into a diamond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-refine-good-at&quot;&gt;What is Refine good at?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Transforming data, either on individual cells or whole columns at a time&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Clustering data to find similar values that repeat for exploration and cleaning&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And many, many other tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refine does a lot of really amazing things, and this class will give you just a tiny taste. It can help high-level programmers with repetitive tasks, and it has its own expression language for accessing and scrubbing data. But it is also a great tool for the less technical set. If you’re comfortable with Microsoft Excel, you should be right at home with Refine. You don’t have to be a comp sci PhD to love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two big areas we’re going to concentrate on today are clustering data and transforming it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s get started. Here are instructions&lt;a href=&quot;http://code.google.com/p/google-refine/wiki/InstallationInstructions&quot;&gt; to install Refine&lt;/a&gt; on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll start with a dataset of lottery winners from New Jersey. Say you want to know what areas spend the most on lottery tickets but win the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download &lt;a href=&quot;/files/2012/06/lotterywinners.csv&quot;&gt;the lottery dataset here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refine runs through your web browser, but don’t worry, it works offline as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can import a table file in many formats, either from your computer, from Google Docs or from a URL for a file on the web. Once you have Refine running, click “Create Project.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll see a preview of what the data looks like. When you pull in the CSV of lottery data, make sure to uncheck the “Parse cell data…” option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/importcsv.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;importcsv&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Jersey zip codes start with zero. If Refine guesses that column is a number, it will drop the leading zero, so unchecking the option will preserve the zips as text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this data, we’re going to use Refine to clean up the W_TOWN column to standardize the names of municipalities. But we never want to work with the raw data, so let’s copy the column that we’ll actually transform into something usable. So click on the arrow at the top of the W_TOWN column and choose the Edit Column&amp;gt;Add column based on this column option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter a name for the new column. We’ll use “TOWN.” Original, I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/copycolumn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;copycolumn&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, initially Refine will only display 10 rows, but there are 3,100 in this dataset, so let’s look at a for more. Click the number 50 next to “Show as” to see more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Excel, one of the first things you’d do with a dataset is sort it. So click on the arrow at the top of the TOWN column and choose “Sort” from the options. Now,  you can filter out just a few records. Click on the arrow and choose “Text Filter” from the options. You’ll see a box pop up in the left column. Type in Atlantic and see how it plucks out only the towns with “Atlantic” in the name: Atlantic City, Atlantic Highlands, Atlantic High and West Atlantic City. As you might guess, not all of these are real towns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s lose the filter. Click on the X in the upper left corner of the filter box. Now, we’re going to add a Facet&amp;gt; Text facet. Dan Nguyen at ProPublica calls Refine’s faceting “the better way to filter.” He’s totally right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facet will create a box in the left column with the total number of choices and a list of all the possible choices in this column and the number of each. You’ll see there are 608 options. At the top is “ABERDEEN” with 3 occurrences. Scroll to the bottom and click on “Facet by choice counts.” This will create another box that will let you display only the choices that occur a certain number of times. It shows the range of values in a column and helps you to spot anomalies or outliers. For instance, if you move the boundaries to only show the choices with between 120 and 140 uses, you’ll only see “JERSEY CITY” and “NEWARK” rows. Close the “Facet by choice counts” box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scroll through the text facet box a little ways into the Bs. See the option for “BELEE MEAD”? It has one occurrence. Notice that two lines later appears “BELLE MEAD,” the actual name of the town. If you hover over “BELEE MEAD,” you will see the option to “edit” appear to the right. Click on that and then fix the spelling of the name in the box that appears. Notice that the choice count drops to 607.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/facet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;facet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at another way to clean data. Scroll down a few more lines. Notice that there are two lines in a row for “BERKELEY HEIGHTS.” They’re spelled the same, so why are they listed separately? Because one of them has an extra space at the end of it that screws up the grouping. This is the kind of thing that back in the bad old days would make you throw your PC out the window two weeks into a data project. Instead, let’s get rid of all the extra, invisible spaces. Click at the top of the TOWN column, edit cells&amp;gt; common transforms&amp;gt; Trim leading and trailing whitespace. Notice again how the choice count dropped. We’re down to 573 town names now. We’re getting there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you could spend hours scrolling through and eyeballing similar names and editing them by hand using these methods, or we could unleash the real power of Refine: clustering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the “Cluster” button in the facet box. Click it and you’ll see something like this. The default method is “key collision.” That should only show a couple of options. Try changing it to “nearest neighbor.” I can’t exactly explain the algorithm behind it, but it’s obvious that it finds town names with similar names that should probably have the same name. You see similar sets like “POMPTON LAKES” and “POMPTON LAKE” or “E. ORANGE,” “E ORANGE” and “E.ORANGE.” Click the “merge” button next to each grouping and type the name you want them all to be changed to in the “New Cell Value” column and hit the “Merge selected and recluster” button at the bottom. You’ve just cleaned those messy columns to a single value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/cluster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cluster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scroll through the list, reclustering and editing whole chunks at a time. This is a huge time saver. When you’re done with the “nearest neighbor” clusters, experiment with “key collision” and see if it picks up any other similar names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, keep in mind that to get this right, you’ll have to do some additional reporting. You’ll need to be certain that “NORTH BRUNSWICK” and “NPRTH BRUNSWICK” are indeed the same place and not separate values as they came to you. If you’re confident in your reporting, Refine makes the data cleaning easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re satisfied that you’re done, click on “Export” on the upper right corner. You can output the file as html, TSV, CSV, Excel or any number of formats. Pull it into your favorite spreadsheet program and run your analysis. Then run it all again to make sure you got it right. To be certain, start from scratch and triple-check it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As cool as this is, Refine has a few more tricks for the beginner. Let’s look at this file of &lt;a href=&quot;/files/2012/06/nj-hospital-2012.xls&quot;&gt;NJ hospital report cards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a new project and import it into Refine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything look weird? How about that first column. Seems like it includes information we’d probably want to split into several columns. In Excel you’d do this with a series of nested functions. In Refine, we can do it with a single click. At the top of the “Hospital” column, choose the drop-down menu and Edit column&amp;gt;Split into several columns…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the wizard menu pops up, choose  a semicolon as the separator and uncheck “remove this column,” because we always want to be compare against our original data, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/splitcolumns.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;splitcolumns&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this looks better, with the name, street, town, state and zip code in separate columns. But something isn’t quite right. What about the zip code? Why is it only four digits? Oh yeah, New Jersey zip codes start with zeroes. Refine assumed that column was an integer and lopped off the zero at the front.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great feature of Refine is that it logs everything you do with the dataset. When you make a mistake or you want track back through your work, click on the “Undo/Redo” tab at the top of the left column and you can tiptoe back through your process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the list and click on the item at the top, “0. Create project” to jump back to that step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/undo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;undo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, redo the “Split into several columns…” step and this time uncheck “Guess cell type” to preserve the zips as text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to make note of the undo option at the top of the screen. You can move a single step back at any time by clicking on this, much like the undo prompt that appears in Gmail after you archive or delete a message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, notice that the names of the hospital are inconsistent. Some are all uppercase. Others are only upper-cased. Let’s standardize them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click on the arrow at the top of the Hospital column and choose Edit cells&amp;gt; Common transforms &amp;gt; To titlecase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/titlecase.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;titlecase&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voila. A cleaned dataset. You’re welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s try one last dataset, this one looking at contributions from &lt;a href=&quot;/files/2012/06/nassau_police_union_contribs.xls&quot;&gt;Nassau County, N.Y. police unions&lt;/a&gt; to political candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Import the data into Refine and let’s start by trying to clean up the town names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add a text facet to the City column. Click Edit cells&amp;gt; Common transforms&amp;gt; trim leading and trailing whitespace&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the count change from 240 to 238.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s cluster the city names to see if we can consolidate any entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/copcluster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;copcluster&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you see the count change in the city column?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s turn our attention to the Name column. For this exercise, let’s start by adding a filter on the city and just looking at “Albany.” You can also do this by clicking on Albany in the text facet box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind  that any changes we make from here on out will only affect the “Albany” subset of the data until we clear this filter (or facet). Now, add a text facet to the “Name” column. Browse the first few entries. Notice there are a lot of very, very similar names here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of argument, let’s say we’re interested in looking at how much Sen. Joe Bruno got from Nassau police groups. There appear to be 10 groups here with similar names receiving donations for Bruno. Seems like a good chance that many of these are the same organization. For the sake of argument, let’s say your reporting shows that yes, these are the same group and we want them to all have the same name for our analysis. Hover your cursor over each one and when the option to “include” appears on the right, click it. Once you’ve “included” them all, click the cluster button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2012/06/subfacet.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;subfacet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will attempt to cluster the choices just in this selection to offer suggestions on names that could b the same. Change the method to “nearest neighbor” and the distance function to “PPM.” If you merge all of the offered suggestions under the same name, it will condense six of the 10 choices into one name. Then you can merge and re-cluster. Once you clean up all the suggestions, you can browse the data in the facet one last time and clean up any stragglers individually as needed. Believe it or not, Refine has just saved you a massive amount of time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-we-learn-here-today&quot;&gt;What did we learn here today?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Refine is a huge time saver and allows you to do commonly tedious data cleaning tasks with a few clicks of the mouse. We saw how to:
- Import and export data.
- Copy and edit columns, trimming whitespaces or changing the capitalization.
- Use facets to filter and edit data
- Cluster a column to standardize spellings and entries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a whirlwind sprint through this program, but hopefully it’s given you a taste of what it can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ideal world, we’d get all of our data handed to us perfectly clean in easy to access, user-friendly, real time feeds that make for simple analysis and display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But until then, we’re going to have to wrestle with the murky and messy datasets produced by those infinite monkeys making an infinite number of mistakes. Use Refine as your new big gun and never give up the fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And remember, if you let the monkeys who enter data into government spreadsheets win, this is where it will lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://blogs-images.forbes.com/toddessig/files/2011/08/planetoftheapesending.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’ll make a monkey out of you too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you want to keep messing with Refine, here are a pair of tutorials that put it much better than I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Huynh, Refine’s creator: &lt;a href=&quot;http://davidhuynh.net/spaces/nicar2011/tutorial.pdf&quot;&gt;http://davidhuynh.net/spaces/nicar2011/tutorial.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Nguyen of ProPublica: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dannguyen.github.com/NICAR-Google-Refine/&quot;&gt;http://dannguyen.github.com/NICAR-Google-Refine/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tip of the hat to &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/lizdday&quot;&gt;Liz Day of ProPublica&lt;/a&gt; for demanding more Simpsons and suggesting I add Troy McClure’s star turn in “Stop the Planet of the Apes, I want to get off!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/clean-data-is-the-best-weapon-against-the-planet-of-the-apes.html&quot;&gt;Clean data is the best weapon against the monkey insurrection&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on June 15, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Checklist to bulletproof your data work]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/checklist.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/checklist</id>
  <published>2012-06-03T10:30:27-04:00</published>
  <updated>2012-06-03T10:30:27-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Updated on 6/23&lt;/strong&gt;: I’ve included, marked by an asterisk, several fantastic checklist suggestions offered by David Donald at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ire.org/blog/2012-ire-conference-blog/&quot;&gt;IRE ‘12 conference&lt;/a&gt; in Boston.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like surgeons, journalists who work with data can always use help ensuring they’re getting things right. I compiled this checklist of questions I ask myself whenever I work with a data set. It’s evolved into a tool that The Star-Ledger data team uses on every story we write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Where did the data come from?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who created it? Is this the best source for this data? What was the methodology behind its collection?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What documentation came with it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you read the documentation? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there a record layout or data dictionary?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you save an original copy of the database if you need to retrace your steps?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are your field headings accurate? Do you have the columns labeled correctly?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you looking at the correct tab? Is there additional data in other tabs in the worksheet?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How many records are in your table or database? How many should be there? Are there any missing? Too many? Any chance you maxed out the number of fields the software can handle?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there duplicates in the records? * &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examine each column of data one at a time. Is it formatted in the appropriate manner? Are there any gaps in the column? Are any data missing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have names and entities been cleaned and standardized? * &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Check the aggregation. How was it done? * &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When joining tables, are you certain the join worked? How many records are there now? Too many? Not enough?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When pasting tables with common columns side-by-side in Excel, do they line up? Any chance two records might be switched?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What calculation are you trying to do? Are you using the appropriate formula or function for this task?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do your cell/column references in functions point to the right places? Are any columns transposed? Can you trace the formula’s path? Have you pasted the correct formula all the way down the column to the bottom of the table?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When sorting, did you sort the entire table together and not omit any columns?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When pasting, is it a good idea to Paste Special&amp;gt;Values to strip out any pesky underlying formulas that may become misdirected?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When moving columns, were there any $ anchors that you pasted that now point to the wrong column or row of data and throw off your calculations?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does your calculation make sense?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you looking at outliers or values in the middle of the pack? * &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there an expert–either an agency data guru or academic–who has  vetted your process or calculations?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have you verified your records against the original records or a sample thereof? * &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have you spot-checked individual records to ensure the numbers match up? Did you ask a colleague to assist by reading off numbers to be CQ’d?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have you asked an uninvolved colleague to look at your process, review the numbers and poke holes in the methodology?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you reproduce your calculations from the beginning or explain step-by-step how you arrived at your conclusion? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What numbers are you using in the story? Have you circled them and reviewed them in the database? Is the description of the numbers accurate? Does it omit any pertinent details that might mislead an unwary reader?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are the numbers here based on counting, estimates, projections or guesses? * &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there any graphics with the story? Have you checked them? Can you verify every number? Are the introduction and column heads accurate? Are there numbers missing from the graphic that are important to the story?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there a methodology/nerd box to run with the story? * &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How did you get here, and does it make sense?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Print &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/11TuHI2rKGFB2IJh_Hvmu5hQgoR4OxpjTwTr4cditOPg/edit?hl=en&amp;amp;authkey=CJTC1YEJ&quot;&gt;a copy of the checklist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you bulletproof your data work? At the 2012 NICAR conference in St. Louis, Tom Johnson and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/cephillips&quot;&gt;Cheryl Phillips&lt;/a&gt; led a seminar discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://skydrive.live.com/?cid=CA060AF0B8AF9A15&amp;amp;id=CA060AF0B8AF9A15!110#cid=CA060AF0B8AF9A15&amp;amp;id=CA060AF0B8AF9A15!199&quot;&gt;their tips for validating data&lt;/a&gt;. I’d really like to hear any advice or ideas you’re willing to share. Leave a comment here with your techniques or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/ultracasual&quot;&gt;tweet at me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A * indicates questions added after hearing David Donald speak about bulletproofing CAR work at IRE ‘12 in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2012/06/checklist.html&quot;&gt;Checklist to bulletproof your data work&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on June 03, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Help Wanted]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2011/06/help-wanted.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2011/06/help-wanted</id>
  <published>2011-06-24T15:12:32-04:00</published>
  <updated>2011-06-24T15:12:32-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We have a job opening up on our CAR team here at The Star-Ledger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not even going to try to compete with Matt Doig’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://motherjones.tumblr.com/post/4046557808/the-best-journalism-job-want-ad-ever-ever&quot;&gt;hilarious&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poynter.org/latest-news/romenesko/124910/im-just-mystified-that-this-little-job-post-has-resonated-with-so-many-people-in-the-business/&quot;&gt;infamous&lt;/a&gt; job post, but I will preface this by saying the Ledger is a very good place to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve got great journalists here who make a habit of exposing the mind-boggling arrogance, greed, incompetence and corruption of the Garden State’s public officials. One of our colleagues just &lt;a href=&quot;http://amyellisnutt.com/&quot;&gt;won a Pulitzer&lt;/a&gt; in feature writing for her investigation of the sinking of a small fishing vessel that killed six men. We’re led by top-notch editors who care about writing and about watchdog journalism that gets results.  My (relatively) new team is starting to do some cool work, and we have an ambitious agenda for the year ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking for strong candidates &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;soon&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Please pass this along to anyone you think might be qualified. Here’s the job description:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The Star-Ledger is looking for a journalist to fill an entry-level position on its computer-assisted reporting team. The reporter will be responsible for acquiring and analyzing public records and data to support enterprise stories for print and online. He or she should be comfortable filing public records and freedom of information requests with agencies at the local, state and federal levels. The reporter will also contribute to the redesign and maintenance of NJ By The Numbers, our home for databases and statistics vital to New Jersey readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Qualifications: A background in local or investigative reporting for a daily news outlet and an affinity for math, web development and programming. Ability to identify and mine public databases for stories large and small and to build and manage relational databases. Experience displaying data graphically in print and online to engage readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proficiency with Microsoft Excel and Access, SQL, HTML and CSS, ESRI ArcView and Google Maps. Bonus points for candidates who have experience or interest in scraping, scripting, frameworks (Django, Rails, ASP.Net) or statistical analysis with SPSS, SAS or R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested, send me a cover letter, resume and clips to my work email, tmeagher(at)starledger(dot)com.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2011/06/help-wanted.html&quot;&gt;Help Wanted&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on June 24, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacks, Cops and the Internet]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2011/05/cops-and-social-media.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2011/05/cops-and-social-media</id>
  <published>2011-05-20T11:50:46-04:00</published>
  <updated>2011-05-20T11:50:46-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About six months ago now, I started a new job, taking over as The Star-Ledger’s Computer-Assisted Reporting Editor. For anyone who follows me on Twitter, this may help explain why many of my online comments lately have dealt with statistics, data visualizations and programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a slight departure from my day-to-day role working with numbers, I was asked to fill in for one of my bosses at a symposium hosted by John Jay College’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jjay.cuny.edu/centers/media_crime_justice/3411.htm&quot;&gt;Center on Media, Crime and Justice&lt;/a&gt;. The round table discussion brought together police and journalists from across New Jersey to talk about working together and how using social media tools can help all of us do our jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an interesting day to say the least. I sat in a room with 45 cops, reporters and editors who often have an adversarial relationship. I met cops who my reporters have been interviewing for years, as well as competitors whose bylines I knew well. It was refreshing to step out of the daily grind for a few hours and talk about our shared frustrations and how we can do things better, particularly with the explosion of social media tools at our fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the jump, some of my prepared remarks, without the slight diversions I took when I delivered them.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-the-public-and-the-news-media-want-from-the-police-on-the-internet&quot;&gt;What the public and the news media want from the police on the internet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Speed. Like news organizations and police departments everywhere, we have seen our resources dwindle. At the same time, competition has grown exponentially. We want the information fast. We want to know what’s happening before it happens and then we want to be able to alert our readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can buy police departments time. If you get a tweet out quickly to alert the public or confirm or deny an event, then you can avoid calls from dozens of media outlets hounding you in the short term. It’ll give you breathing room to gather the facts on the investigation before responding to follow-up questions or releasing more details. We know the scanner chatter is often wrong, but often we can’t afford not to chase a story unless the police confirm that it’s wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tweet is a starting point. It can be a great way to immediately alert a lot of people to a major news issue (a high-profile arrest) or a public safety or infrastructure concern (tunnel closing, fire or tornado). But there needs to be….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Interaction. The nature of the internet has changed communication. It is not a one-way platform. For it to have any relevance, you have to interact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People will come to you looking for answers. if you don’t provide them, lots of other people on the internet will try to fill in the gaps, often with misinformation. A tweet from a passerby that says something like, “I drove by a fire on Main St., and it looks like a plane hit a house. It’s carnage everywhere.” could have just been a small kitchen fire that sent lots of smoke into a residential street. There is no replacement for an investigation from the authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will inevitably raise a number of questions in departments large and small: Who is in charge of the Twitter feed? Who is empowered to post on it? Is there a policy for replying to tweets or Facebook comments? It can be time consuming to keep up to date. But a social media presence isn’t particularly useful as simply an archive of static press releases. (As I learned at the event, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iacpsocialmedia.org/&quot;&gt;International Association of Chiefs of Police Center on Social Media&lt;/a&gt; has drafted &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iacpsocialmedia.org/GettingStarted/PolicyDevelopment.aspx&quot;&gt;a model policy&lt;/a&gt; for law enforcement agencies on how to adopt social media tools).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being on the internet has to be faster than telling reporters that they have to wait three days to talk to the designated PIO about a homicide (which we hear far more often than one would expect). And posting a single statement online isn’t sufficient. It’s a good place to start so we know what kind of story we’re dealing with, but we need to be able to follow up. We need to be able to ask questions to clarify statements and probe for more detail. You don’t have to answer all of the questions, but we need to be able to ask them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t want to ever have to attribute information to an agency’s website or Twitter feed. We use these as planning tools. Then we want to confirm the information with a real person in the department to make sure we got it right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the police can use these social media platforms to their advantage. The LAPD used Twitter to seek information in a hit and run of a valet at a restaurant, for instance. They later arrested an elderly man in the case, although it’s not clear if the tip that led to his arrest came from a Twitter user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/#!/njsp&quot;&gt;NJ State Police&lt;/a&gt; has used Twitter to dispel rumors and bad information from scanner reports about a plane crash in South Jersey or SEALs training in the Delaware River. They’ve also used it to get out initial information on fatal accidents and crimes before being bombarded by reporters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The internet is just a tool. If your department or PIO refuses to share public information with the public, then there’s no point in being online. You have to have information that people want for it to be worthwhile. Posting about park closures or issues of minor significance are not good enough. Users on social media, particularly Twitter and Facebook are voracious news consumers. They want substance and lots of it. If you’re not answering phone calls from reporters who need information, there’s no reason you’d do it online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of encouraging an air of transparency in your department however is that it can help demystify the process of police work and humanize law enforcement officers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Facebook and Twitter can also be investigative tools. When we background a subject of a story, a crime or otherwise, these sites are among the first things we look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In several cases in New Jersey lately, it’s been a key component of criminal charges against young people. In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2010/09/hold_new_rutgers_post.html&quot;&gt;Tyler Clementi case&lt;/a&gt;, his former roommate is charged with trying to doctor his Twitter account to remove incriminating information. In the case of a group of Old Bridge teens accused of beating a man to death, they allegedly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2010/11/teens_bragged_about_beating_of.html&quot;&gt;held extensive conversations on Facebook&lt;/a&gt; about the night in question and the beating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;and-it-helps-us-track-people-down-like-the-hoboken-woman-who-shot-the-amazing-picture-of-the-space-shuttlehttpwwwnjcomnewsindexssf201105hobokenwomansiphonephotosohtml-from-the-window-of-her-airplane-we-found-her-on-facebook&quot;&gt;And it helps us track people down, like the Hoboken woman who shot &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nj.com/news/index.ssf/2011/05/hoboken_womans_iphone_photos_o.html&quot;&gt;the amazing picture of the Space Shuttle&lt;/a&gt; from the window of her airplane. We found her on Facebook.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My talk went well, although it was a bit disconcerting to notice that one of my fellow panelists, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/#!/MPLASD&quot;&gt;Capt. Mike Parker&lt;/a&gt; of the Los Angeles County Sheriff’s Department, was looking up &lt;a href=&quot;http://linkedin.com/in/tommeagher&quot;&gt;my resume&lt;/a&gt; on his laptop as I spoke. Even though I post all these things to the whole world on the internet, it’s easy to forget sometimes that anyone actually looks at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the day’s discussions offered a good opportunity to see some of these sources in a less-heated environment and learn from the other attendees and panelists (including Ted Gest of &lt;a href=&quot;http://reporters.net/cjj/whoweare.html&quot;&gt;Criminal Justice Journalists&lt;/a&gt; and Nancy Kolb of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theiacp.org/&quot;&gt;International Association of Chiefs of Police&lt;/a&gt;) about some of the resources we all have at our fingertips. I found out about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thecrimereport.org/&quot;&gt;The Crime Report&lt;/a&gt;, put together by Criminal Justice Journalists and The Center on Media, Crime and Justice. I also heard about IACP’s handy directory of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iacpsocialmedia.org/Directory.aspx&quot;&gt;police agencies with a presence on social media&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the best reminder I heard all day though came from one of the other panelists, &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/#!/CaptainJeffPaul&quot;&gt;Capt. Jeff Paul&lt;/a&gt;, public information officer for the Morris County Prosecutor’s Office.  He bristled at receiving calls from reporters asking for information, in some cases demanding answers, without ever coming to introduce themselves to him. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with all of this magic from the interwebs to help us communicate faster and easier, there really is no replacement for building a personal relationship, face-to-face, with a police source, before you’re on deadline in the middle of a catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leave a comment below or follow me on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/ultracasual/&quot;&gt;@ultracasual&lt;/a&gt; and tell me about your experience working with police or journalists on social media networks.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2011/05/cops-and-social-media.html&quot;&gt;Hacks, Cops and the Internet&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on May 20, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Story Tips Short And Long]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2010/10/story-tips-short-and-long.html" />
  <id>http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2010/10/story-tips-short-and-long</id>
  <published>2010-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</published>
  <updated>2010-10-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Tom Meagher</name>
    <uri>http://www.tommeagher.com</uri>
    <email>hello+site@tommeagher.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;1.Write tight. Maybe the most important thing you can do to increase your productivity without doing more work is to write tight and trim your own work. Write briefs instead of 8 inchers. Write 8 inchers instead of 10 inchers. Write 10-12s instead of 12-15s. Write 12-15s instead of 15-18s. The tighter you write, the less time it takes and the more time you free up for other stuff. Time is a gift to the news reporter. Use that extra hour or half hour to stop in on your beat, talk to a couple sources on the phone, read online what other newspapers are doing, or skim-read documents or reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​2. Prewrite/outline. Whether you sweat over your copy or it flows from your fingers like hot fudge, prewriting saves you time and energy. Take five to 10 minutes before you start to think how am I going to handle my story. Look at your notes and materials. Make yourself a thumbnail outline. What’s your lede? What’s your best quote(s)? What’s the news important to readers? What’s the background? What’s the context? Once you’ve got a bijou outline, you’ve got a roadmap. Drive, she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​3. Demand coaching. Editors know they need to story conference and coach writing and help with resources and ideas, but things get hectic and sometimes they don’t. That does not mean you should not ask advice and coaching. The crucial times to talk to an editor are: before you start reporting; after you finish reporting, but before you start writing; when you’ve got a top; and, of course, when you have to make a late decision on whether the story holds up, reaching an alternate source, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.Master the art of the weekbook. It can’t be said too often or emphasized too much: the weekbook is the key to excellent and efficient performance. At its basic level, the weekbook is a scheduling device. To take your weekbook to a higher level of value requires the additional ingredient: forethought. Here are several specific practices that can improve your weekbook - as well as your editors’ esteem and your job satisfaction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a good mix of stories every week. No one wants to do the same thing day after day. Build concise dailies around news events, meetings, issues. Build in patches (centerpieces) by thinking what will make a good photo story. Build a weekend story every week by giving yourself a couple hours early to midweek to report, a day or three quarters day midweek to late week to write. Build in overnights with a 2 p.m. deadline, freeing up an afternoon for weekend story or enterprise work. Put in a strong daily Monday to anchor the week and a timeless news feature, profile or human interest story later in the week, that can be used on the weekend.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;News stories break like waves. It’s coming (preview), it breaks (hard news) and recedes (impact, folo, news feature, analysis, preview of next stage). Think of that wave shape. Ride the wave and you’ll get three or more hits off one news event.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add a line called FOLO beneath every budget line in your weekbook. After you’ve finished your story, go back and give yourself leads to follow up: sources not reached, questions unanswered on deadline, possible profiles of people in the news, impact of an event, stories that ask why? And how? instead of just who, what, where and when. Readers’ surveys often indicate that one of the things readers dislike is hit and miss coverage, especially one day wonders. Readers want closure. They want the rest of the story. Use the FOLO line to help fill your next weekbook.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make your weekbook a living document. Go back and change it, add to it, as the week goes along. It only takes a minute. Then re-mine that weekbook in subsequent weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you know you are going to be working on a weekend, start talking to your weekend editor about your story early in the week. There’s nothing more awful than a reporter in panic on Thursday afternoon with no idea what to cover on Saturday or Sunday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​4. Team up with colleagues. It’s challenging, it’s fun, it’s productive. And it gives readers from various towns some sense of how news cuts across municipal boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​5. Keep a tickler file, aka a futures file; fill it with clips, letters, notes, pictures, labels and related junk of every variety from which story ideas will emerge. Review it now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​6. Don’t fall into the rut of thinking there are no good stories on your beat. Instead, try to attack same-old stories from different, imaginative angles. Write more stories on how news impacts our towns and people. Write local trend stories. Write community crime trend stories. Write service pieces that inform readers about things they never thought they wanted to know and help readers make decisions. Write local business pieces. Write local environmental stories. Write more people stories, and especially more profiles. People like to read about people. Put a human face on as many stories as you possibly can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​7. Remember listening posts for increasing the diversity of our sources and scope? Start doing them one day per period, as required. If you can’t do a full day, spend a few hours one day and a few hours another day. Add new sources to your regular news coverage. Add new voices to the mix of sources. The Herald News should never become a city/town hall newspaper!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​8. We can do the short-term investigation. We can do investigations that depend more on human intelligence than massive data analysis. We can reveal sides of life in our coverage area that no one knows. Try to rethink your investigative ambitions. Go for the clean, short, effective strike. Go for the Wow! Factor: the story that makes readers say to themselves, “Wow, I didn’t know that!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​9. Revisit stories. Many reporters know to keep a futures file. Many know to revisit certain stories on a temporal basis (after one year, five years, 10 years etc.). This best practice adds another revisit category: the revisit to the incomplete story. Sometimes, try as we might, we simply cannot get the full story by deadline time. Typically, an important source is missing or evasive. Or an agency delays an answer. Or a document can’t be obtained. There are many forms of this. We go with what we’ve got. But when there’s a significant hole in the article, we owe it to readers to revisit the story as soon as we can and follow up with a second story or brief. This is especially true when the missing information changes the way we covered the story previously. This best practice speaks to both accuracy and thoroughness- two important parts of getting it right, which is our basic contract with readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​10. Morgue. Many of you are checking the digital library for articles going back for years (to 1998) as part of your routine reporting. All of you should be doing this every day. In addition, however, please don’t forget that the library has a paper morgue going back donkey years. It’s a good practice to check this, particularly when articles involve people who don’t show up in the digital. Ask Mauro Margarelli to help you find the files you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​11. Eight Ways to Tell a Story. One of the most useful handouts Warren Watson of API left behind is the one put together by the York Daily Record editor about the local kid who won a dance contest. She wrote the same story in eight different ways, from inverted period to Q&amp;amp;A, to photo package, blocks, narrative and beyond. This is a handy document that all should have and refer to. If you don’t have it, see Jonathan for a copy. If you do have it, use it. God did not hand down the inverted pyramid on stone tablets. Many stories can be told better in other ways. Just as no one likes to eat the exact same thing three times
a day, readers, too, want variety. You can still present serious news information in entertaining ways. It just takes thought, creativity and effort. The reporter’s job is always to make what she finds relevant interesting for the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;compiled from Best Practices written by &lt;em&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/em&gt;, Herald News, from 2002 to 2004&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-story-forms&quot;&gt;New story forms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.Three &lt;strong&gt;Narrative Dailies&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrative journalism is often associated, in journalists’ minds, with lengthy enterprise projects. But there is no law saying narrative techniques cannot be used in dailies or short form. At the recent Niemann Narrative Conference at Harvard, I jotted down three types of daily stories that we could start doing to tell stories in new, interesting and insightful ways for HN readers. Below, three generic budget lines. Use them in good health, with one caveat: narrative doesn’t mean you can make it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TICKTOCK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We take a news event, breaking or second day reporting. Instead of organizing from the most important in the lead to the least important at the end, we reconstruct the event over time. What led up to that explosion? What happened the night that cop was murdered? What did that family do on the day they died in a car crash? Exactly what steps did the mayor take that allowed him to pass a zero increase budget? Or, alternatively, what is the aftermath of a particular news event? What happened minute by minute after the plane crashed? What happened to the freeholder in the days and weeks after he dropped out of third grade?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SECONDDRAFT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Journalism is often called the first draft of history. But the first draft is often abbreviated and cursory, sometimes underreported or skewed, and in some cases, wrong. In this story type, we take a second look at a breaking story, going back to sources for a fuller or better account, taking an unexpected angle or digging out some universal human truth from what at first ran as a brief or rushed deadline piece. The goal is truth, not just facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EXPLAINER&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Narrative methods focusing on one person can often help readers understand complex, novel or unfamiliar issues and processes better than conventional reporting - which often overlooks the explanatory. Bankruptcy. Identity theft. Outsourcing. Uninsured. Poverty level. Daycare. Drug addiction. Productivity. Deregulation. Bond rating. And on and on. In the explainer, we use one person’s story to give readers insight into a hard-to-get-at topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​2. Three types of &lt;strong&gt;profiles&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to think of profiles, if we think of them at all, as one thing: stories about people. It took Bill Blundell, former Page One editor at the Wall Street Journal has three types of profiles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​a. The General Profile: Concentrates on unique qualities of subject, aspects of difference: what makes this person unique, different, outstanding, unusual, unconventional, nontraditional, nonstandard, peculiar, pale and interesting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​b. The Microcosm Profile: centers on aspects of sameness, universality. In what ways is this person or this person’s story typical, universal, human, like all of us? What part of her or her story can we all connect with?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​c. The News Profile: centers on the subject’s connection to a news event. Also could be called, as the Times does (or used to): Man in the News. Person in the News?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/em&gt;, June 2004&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-enterprise-project&quot;&gt;The Enterprise project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our conference call with Cleveland Plain Dealer writer Connie Schultz, she mentioned several methods that helped her narrative series “The Burden of Innocence,” which was the subject of our brown bag writers group. They are excellent practices, not only for narrative journalism, but for any enterprise story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​1) &lt;strong&gt;Write as you go&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schultz said she always transcribed her notes as soon as possible and kept them in files organized by month as she worked on the series over the course of one year. Any project that involves reporting over time benefits from having well-organized notes from interviews and reporting. It puts the writer ahead of the curve when you get down to the business of writing. This practice can be easily extended to the practice of writing themes, sections, scenes, dialogue, good quotes, etc. as you go. Don’t imagine you can wait until you’re reporting is done, then look back at your notebooks or journal and suddenly pull the white rabbit out of the hat. Doesn’t work like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​2) &lt;strong&gt;Writing a Map/ outline&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schultz said that before she started to write, her editor asked for a written map, a term she described as having less onerous associations than outline. The map or outline provides writer and editor with a guide to the story, where it starts, where it goes, what it’s about, where it ends. It makes the writer think. It need not be followed like a
contract. Whatever it’s called, this best practice is one of the quintessential building blocks of longer-length writing. Without it, you are, effectively, roaming around blindfolded, hoping to pin the tail on the donkey. With a roadmap or outline, even if rudimentary (many are the outlines noted on the back of a cocktail napkin; Tolstoy outlined Anna Karenina on a railroad train dining car menu (which, however, later fell behind the sofa at his estate Yasnaya Polyana, forcing him to write War &amp;amp; Peace first instead, but that is another story)).you can focus on the material and how to express it accurately, faily and gracefully, not on what to write next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​3) &lt;strong&gt;Rewriting&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schultz said rewriting was the most painful part– she went through a dozen major drafts. But rewriting is an absolutely necessary practice to achieve successful narratives/enterprise stories. If you are to become a skilled pro writer, you must get past the idea that rewriting means you are doing something wrong. Rewriting is, in fact, doing something right: Improving the story, draft by draft. No story has ever suffered from rewriting. Many suffered from too little rewriting. Just as the map/outline helps the writer through the first draft, the editor’s read and conferencing helps the writer through rewrite. Talk out what needs to be done. Partner. Writers don’t need to accept everything an editor says, like medicine or punishment. Writers do need to defend and articulate something they want to keep. Develop a collaborative rewrite strategy and get to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​4) &lt;strong&gt;Writing buddies&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scultz said she chooses another writer in the newsroom she respects to critique her pieces, so that she has an additional sounding board outside the editors-reporter loop. Practically every mature writer does this, asking colleagues or friends to read the work and tell the brutal truth. However, this practice really depends on choosing someone with
good judgment, analytical skill and the ability to articulate and criticize&amp;gt; constructively. Anything less is less than helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/em&gt;, April 2003&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;edit-proof-copy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/tips/editproofmanual.pdf&quot;&gt;Edit Proof copy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​1. The reporter’s constant focus should be on the question: &lt;strong&gt;what is this story about?&lt;/strong&gt; That helps shape the lede, the angle, the structure, everything. Also, editors should keep reporters focused on this question throughout the day so that the reporter refines and hones the story to present the reader with a tight, concise, well-organized story without
holes, digressions or frills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​2. There’s a natural contradiction between the creative process and critical thinking, between writer or storyteller inside us and the editor or critic inside. The critic suppresses the storyteller and makes it harder for the storyteller to tell the story. That’s why it’s so hard to write a solid lede: every time the storyteller wants to put a thought down, the critic says ,”that stinks,” “that’s not good enough.” So Chip Scanlon talked about “lowering your standards” when you draft your story. I think a better way to say this is to suspend your critical faculties while you are writing your first draft and just get it down using your creative juices. Then switch over to your critical faculties to rewrite, sharpen, trim, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​3. &lt;strong&gt;A topic is not a story&lt;/strong&gt;. You can’t write about AIDS, or mass transit, or affordable housing. Those are topics. A story has to have a beginning, middle and end. It has to have characters. It has to have a plot. It has to have a setting. This is a cogent point. How many times do editors hear from reporters, “I want to write about poverty in Paterson.” “I want to write about the Passaic River.” “I want to write about race relations between latinos and blacks.” How many times do reporters hear from editors: “We should do a story about high property taxes.” Well what about it? Themes are not stories. Think about telling stories. It’s elemental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​4. Words of wisdom from Don Murray, a legendary writing coach, on organizing and “mapping” the reporting and writing of a story: &lt;strong&gt;explore, focus, rehearse, draft, clarify&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​5. Experienced reporters know what is the least amount of reporting they need to do for any given story. Great reporters know there is no limit except deadline for reporting, and that the quality of a story really, truly depends on the reporting, not the writing. If you don’t know as many facts and factoids as you possibly can, the story is going to be thin and pale. Somebody said, “Reporting is taking a beer keg of information and squeezing it into a perfume bottle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​6. A good way to start the process: reporter and editor brainstorm on reader’s questions. What does the reader need to and want to know about the story. That helps the reporter focuse on question above: What is this story about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​7. Rick Bragg’s five boxes. NY Times reporter Rick Bragg learned from a mentor that he should organize and write his stories as if he had five empty boxes floating in the air above him: In the first box, he put the lede or grabber. In the second, the nut graf: what’s this story about. In the third box, tell the story. In the fourth, info, context, back story, etc. And in the fifth, the kicker, the ending, something that leaves
the reader with emotional meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​8. Jack Hart, enterprise editor at The Oregonian: Don’t confuse anecdotes in anecdotal ledes with scenesetters. &lt;strong&gt;Anecdotes are little stories, with their own beginning and end. Scenesetters just get the reader to the right “place.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​9. Get rid of dependent clauses in your sentences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​10. &lt;strong&gt;To revise, you need to achieve distance&lt;/strong&gt;. You can’t plunge right into a revision. You have to take a break, do something else for a while, eat something or drink something, divert your attention, go for a walk, something. Everyone finds their own way to get a distance on his/her own work. Whatever cools the engine down then revs it up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jonathan Maslow&lt;/em&gt;, May 2005&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;story-conception-and-execution&quot;&gt;Story conception and execution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From notes taken during &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.journalism.missouri.edu/faculty/jacqui-banaszynski.html&quot;&gt;Jacqui Banaszynski’s&lt;/a&gt; visit to the Herald
News on Aug. 14, 2004.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to tell people what the news means and what’s its significance. When you get a story assignment, immediately sit down and brainstorm for five minutes. Brainstorm questions, not even to necessarily use in an interview. Anything you think you know, turn it into a question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you want to know?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are you curious about?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who are the stakeholders in the story?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, do this again so you have ideas for second day stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On most stories, you write the first-day story. On the second day, you do a story that’s very wide, takes in all the questions but is not very deep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, do six or seven deep stories of varying types:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Profiles - character-based&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues/trends - ideas, fashion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigative - records-based&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Explanatory - a teachable moment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Descriptive/voices - use telling details&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Narratives - scenes &amp;amp; dialogue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Visuals - using graphics and boxes to tell the story&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editors want a working &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.poynter.org/column.asp?id=52&amp;amp;aid=34457&quot;&gt;nut graf&lt;/a&gt; when you pitch a story. Do some preliminary reporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each editor is looking for something different, get to know each of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a budget line helps you establish goals. Write your working budget line as questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find a colleague who will read your ledes in progress and to discuss story craft with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ledes engage the reader. Don’t misdirect the reader. Lede them with foreshadowing and summarize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the AP, don’t frontload a lot of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lede should signal the tone and voice of the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vary the pacing and rhythm and length of your sentences. Long sentences read fast. Then a short sentance halts the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://poynteronline.org/content/content_view.asp?id=707&quot;&gt;30 Tips from Poynter’s Roy Peter Clark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com/blog/2010/10/story-tips-short-and-long.html&quot;&gt;Story Tips Short And Long&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Tom Meagher at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tommeagher.com&quot;&gt;Tom Meagher&lt;/a&gt; on October 06, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
